<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The parallel, or, The new specious association an old rebellious covenant closing with a disparity between a true patriot and a factious associator.</title>
            <author>Northleigh, John, 1657-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1301</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5814</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13085815</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13085815</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97305</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52460)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97305)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 393:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The parallel, or, The new specious association an old rebellious covenant closing with a disparity between a true patriot and a factious associator.</title>
                  <author>Northleigh, John, 1657-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B. Tooke ... and T. Sawbridge ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by John Northleigh. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97305:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PARALLEL: OR, The New Specious Aſſociation AN
<hi rend="blackletterType">Old Rebellious Covenant.</hi> Cloſing with a Diſparity between A TRUE PATRIOT, AND <hi rend="blackletterType">A Factious Aſſociator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Tooke,</hi> at the
<hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, and <hi>T. Sawbridge,</hi> at the <hi>Three Flower-de-luces</hi> in <hi>Little Brittain,</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:97305:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97305:2"/>
            <head>The Parallel.</head>
            <p>NEver did a piece of Villany deſerve ſharper Animadverſion, or the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver of it more ſeverity; and both I fancy might have had their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts already, did not the groſsneſs of the Treaſon, almoſt ſuperſede reflection, and the greatneſs of the Traytor exempt him from Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo that there is even a ſort of neceſſity ſeverely to reflect on ſuch a horrid Contrivance; as onely by the boldneſs of its being undertaken, ſeems to dare and provoke it; and preſume upon an
<hi>Impunity,</hi> from the very <hi>greatneſs</hi> of its <hi>guilt;</hi> and this enormity of the Subject may ſerve to make this Paper a palatable ſort of ſcribble, though the ſuperfluity of ſo many Pamphlets is enough to make it nauſeous<hi>:</hi> But the Author of it deſires as little to be known, as that of the <hi>Aſſociation;</hi> and therefore comes into the World, as ſome late Criminals out of Priſon, with an <hi>Ignoramus.</hi> But with this advantage, That if the one were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, no Law would make him loſe ſo much as one of his <hi>Ears;</hi> whilſt it would adjudge the other to forfeit his <hi>Head;</hi> I mean thoſe Laws that are ſtill the ſame, though the Juſtice of them be perverted; That Juſtice which our kind Prince diffuſes indeed like a mighty Stream, but is ſtill ſwallowed up in the Gulph of that unfathomable thing, call'd a <hi>Conſcience;</hi> That arrogant conceit of doing well, of doing <hi>God</hi> good ſervice and the <hi>King,</hi> though it be in committing <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> and commencing <hi>Rebel;</hi> That prodigious Paradox, that unintelligible Lump of Contradiction, which now can huddle together a guilty piece of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, make Teaſon a ſpecies of Loyalty; Saint and Rebel, Terms Aequivocal or even Homonymous; and with the moſt unreaſonable part of Logick unite the moſt oppoſite Shapes, patch up a Centaure in imagination; make a fantaſtick Monſter leap up with a thought, and with an extravagant conceit, jumble toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that hotch-potch Animal, that Heterogeneous Compoſition of an
<hi>Honest Knave.</hi> Certainly theſe Dictates of <hi>Conſcience</hi> can now no longer be call'd Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or the ſuggeſtions even of common ſenſe, much leſs he impulſes of a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſoul, (for as ſome rapt Zealots would have them thought,) the Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Infuſions of Enthuſiaſm and Revelation, when they ſhall prepoſterouſly ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the greateſt Criminals innocent, and acquit by the Sentiments of a few Men, thoſe whom almoſt Mankind condemns.</p>
            <p>To reflect here a little on the proceedings of our late
<hi>Juries,</hi> is ſo far perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to this diſcourſe, as they themſelves ſeem a band of covenanting <hi>Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciators,</hi> ſuch as would have acquitted the Factious Inditer of this <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> had they found him muſing on it at his Desk, with an imperfect draught of the bloody Scheme in his hand, and blowing up the Government with his dangerous Ammunition of Pen, Ink, and Paper; ſuch as would have cleard a
<hi>Proteſtant Joyner,</hi> had they ſeized him with his hands on his Majeſty; and would rather reaſon themſelves out of Senſe, then ſuch a Villain out of his Life; and what is the greateſt Paradox, ſtill conceit themſelves <hi>Honeſt-men</hi> and <hi>True,</hi> whatever all the World thinks to the contrary. I fancy ſuch diſaffected creatures will think me but an improper Animadverter on the Subject in hand, who am ſo eaſie and credulous a fool, as to believe the ridiculous deſign of ſeizing his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and the ſtrange Paradox of a <hi>Presbyterian-Plot.</hi> As for the firſt, I will tell theſe merry Gentlemen, they onely make it ridiculous, by laughing at it; and though it is not probable that they would have ſerved his Majeſty like a little diminutive King at Cheſs; huddl'd him up into a Bag, and ſo march't off with the Prize; yet Mr.
<hi>Colledge</hi> had provided, I think, a Sack for him, in his emblematical repreſentations of the Monarchy, and truſſed him upon ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97305:3"/>too in his Pictures; But, to ſpeak ſeriouſly, I can't ſee the ridiculouſneſs of keeping a King Priſoner, till thoſe Bills are extorted into Laws by his Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which were never like to meet with his Royal Aſſent without ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint. And inſtead of thinking ſuch deſigns but the <hi>deliriums</hi> of a crack't Scull, I ſhould rather imagine them the politicks of their hot Brains: eſpecially when the proceedings of their very Fore-fathers, makes them ſo good States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and tickles the young Heirs, with the pleaſant thoughts how bravely their Grandſires domineer'd with their Propoſals, o're the poor Prince at
<hi>Holmby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then my thoughts of the <hi>Presbyterian-Plot</hi> are briefly thus. That though we cannot detect any private Commiſſions to raiſe Forces; yet we have as much ground to believe it as the <hi>Popiſh</hi> one, in which there has not one Commiſſion been found amongſt all the ſeiz'd Papers, notwithſtanding ſo many ſworn to be delivered; and this I urge, not as detracting from the certainty of the latter, the Generals of which I believe as much as my Creed, but onely to ſhew that ſuch Gentlemen ought not to be ſo partial to their own Cauſe, as to make that an argument in their own defence, which by no means they can allow in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's. And there may be a complicated Conſpiracy, though not proved with an actual Rebellion, and which I am apt to believe has been carrying on, ever ſince the death of the <hi>Protector,</hi> as well as the other ever ſince the deceaſe of Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> but however, if I miſtake not, we have of late met with many detecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their overt-acts, to ſubvert the Government, beſides thoſe by-tricks of Libelling, and defaming it; witneſs only, this
<hi>Aſſociation</hi> at preſent, becauſe 'tis to be the ſubject of this Diſcourſe; And now I believe they underſtand of what kind of Principles I am compos'd of, what Sentiments I have of their <hi>Plots,</hi> which whether rational or no, they muſt not Judge becauſe Party: and then what wonder is it, if the detection of their Conſpiracies, and the Puniſhment of the Delinquents be ſo difficult to be compaſs'd, when both muſt lye in the breaſt of ſuch as ſeem to eſpouſe the Priſoner's Cauſe, and with a reſolved ſort of incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity to believe neither Evidence on Oath, matter of Fact, or their own Sences? What wonder is it if His Majeſty, cannot have the Common Juſtice they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute to their private ſelves; to every <hi>Tyler,</hi> or <hi>Jack Straw,</hi> that has but a Property to a Stall, a Shop, a Tool, or a green Apron; when theſe Gentlemen of the Yard and Tool, themſelves muſt decide the Controverſie; who I warrant you will be ſure to take more care of their own <hi>Propertie,</hi> than of his <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive?</hi> But are theſe all the thankful Acknowledgments His Majeſty muſt expect for His Gracious Charter? Muſt the <hi>King</hi>'s Enemies be ſpar'd, becauſe the <hi>Cities</hi> Friends? Muſt he by giving, paſs himſelf into a <hi>Donative?</hi> By his own Grant, ſeclude himſelf from the benefit of the very Laws he gives
<hi>Life</hi> too? And muſt thoſe Immunities, and Priviledges he gives them for their Liberty, be uſed by thoſe ungrateful Wretches as <hi>Spoils</hi> and <hi>Trophies</hi> of his <hi>Prerogative?</hi> Certainly from ſuch Proceedings as theſe, what other deduction can be made by ſober thoughts, but that they declare an open defiance to the Government; that they will ſtand to their City Charter, and their Arms together; and ſeal it juſt as the Great one was by the Barons in <hi>Blood?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From thoſe partial interpretations of Guilt and Innocence, what can an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different perſon think, but that the abuſed name of
<hi>Conſcience,</hi> is applied on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now to the Capriciouſneſs of Fancy; ſubjects only Patriots and Rebels, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diverſity of thought?</p>
            <p>The King a Nurſing Father, as long as his politick Sons will think him ſo; transform'd into a <hi>Tyra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as ſoon as they pleaſe to conceit otherwiſe; the naked Hulk of the Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>l'd by Popiſh Pyrates, when every froward Fool does not ſit at the He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nd the Convocation of the Church, a Conclave of Cardinals, when each diſſenting Aſs can't commence a Prolocutor. I have obſerv'd the Seat and Empire of the Soul, or at leaſt the ſeveral Faculties of it, by the grave Sages in Philoſophy, to have been confin'd to ſuch Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Body, as were moſt adapted for the Faculty that was to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erted in it; and accordingly, Reaſon is circumſcribed within the Compaſs of the <hi>Meditullium,</hi> and Sphere of the Brain; the Appetitive Soul placed in<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97305:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Breaſt; the Senſitive in the Nerves; and all Paſſion in the Heart. If theſe are warrantable conjectures, I don't ſee but I may with as much Reaſon, and Philoſophy, place ſome Mens <hi>Conſciences</hi> in their Stomachs; becauſe it is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the help of its Fibres, to contract, or dilate it ſelf, according as the more ſcrupulous, or bolder Animal, ſhall direct his intentions; oft ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at a Gnat, as if it were to take a Potion; whilſt Camels and Elephants are ſwallowed without a Grimace, and go down like their Sack-poſſet: This helps them to ſlip down Oaths, with a more than <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> dexterity; to make an Explanation of a Teſt, after it is in their Bellies; or if it will not digeſt with that prepoſterous piece of Cookery, 'tis but playing a Jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler's trick, and bringing it up like their pieces of Inkle; ſometimes imitating the ſqueamiſh Maw of a Cormorant, taught to throw up all; ſometimes that of another ſort of Fowl, which is ſaid to concoct Iron and Stones; And all this irreconcilable proceeding, carried on without the leaſt Diſpenſation of
<hi>Reaſon,</hi> or <hi>Religion;</hi> and conſequently leſs warrantable than the damn'd Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations of <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> their blind opinion of ſome Supream Powers, Abſolution, and Indulgence, ſomewhat extenuates the guilt of thoſe perjur'd Villains; whilſt every Man's prejudiced Opinion, pretends here to be its own abſolver; the ſole Meaſures of all Guilt, and Innocence; and the Lawful Standard both to good and bad actions: And then, what wonder is it, if the Proceedings of the
<hi>King,</hi> and the Advice of his <hi>Council,</hi> are expoſed as light and empty; when they muſt be weighed in the pois'd Ballance of every pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced Noddle, that has but one grain of Sence more, of Loyalty leſs, than his liſt'ning Rabble; the reſult of whoſe judgment is Reverenc'd as an Oracle, by the ſilly Rout, each Seditious expreſſion treaſur'd up as a politick Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm, and the bold Dictator like a pleaſant piece of Pageantry, riding Cock-horſe on the Shoulders of the Mobile; in a confus'd noiſe of Shouts and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, and all the wild Repreſentations of a diſtracted People.</p>
            <p>I hope by this Preliminary diſcourſe, to have prevented the farther peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of the reſt, by any that find themſelves gall'd, or prick't, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciouſneſs of their meriting any of the paſt reflexions; for ſuch perſons though partial enough to themſelves, hard to be perſwaded, eſpecially of any thing that looks like <hi>Guilty,</hi> are commonly a little troubled to be thought ſo; and for ſuch diſaffected Readers, 'tis a kindneſs both to them and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, to be civilly nettled in the beginning, leſt by a gentler ſtile, they ſhould be decoy'd to the end; and then rail at him with as much rage, and indignation, as they uſe againſt the Government; Chriſten him for a Popiſh Dog, and
<hi>Iriſh</hi> Bogg-Trotter; when otherwiſe, perhaps, he may eſcape with the gentler Animadverſions of a Malicious Aſs, and Scribling Fool.</p>
            <p>But the harſheſt of ſuch peoples Judgment, and Cenſure, will be ſuperſeded by their own ignorance or prejudice; and this Paper allow'd to ſpeak <hi>Truth,</hi> though it don't carry in its Front an impudent <hi>Lye,</hi> or a <hi>Vox Veritatis;</hi> thought to have ſomewhat of Judgment and Reaſon in it, though not ſubſcrib'd by a <hi>Theophilus Rationalis.</hi> Thoſe Juggling tricks of putting off Lies, and Nonſenſe, and making the firſt Page a <hi>Confutation</hi> of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>And now to begin with this complicated piece of Rebellion, ſmoothly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on, under the ſpecious name of an
<hi>Aſſociation;</hi> the Method I ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, ſhall as much as poſſible, make the Contents correſpond with the Title Page, and not, like ſome, let the firſt Leaf quarrel with the whole Pamphlet. And,</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>We ſhall ſhew the moſt undeniable agreeableneſs of this Aſſociation, with all the old Leagues, and Covenants; in circumſtances of Time, and Affairs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> II. <hi>Their affinity in Matter, Form, and Words, and draw the Parallel</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97305:4"/>
                  <hi>even to Demonstration; with a little Comment on each Paragraph: And anſwering Objections, they uſe to defend it:</hi>
               </item>
               <item> And laſtly, <hi>Shew the diſparity between a True Patriot, and a Factious Aſſociator; and that his expelling the Duke, is no ſuch Evidence of his loving his Countrey.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>That this Paper was penn'd at a time, when the unhappy Differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King, and his Commons were in their higheſt ferment; won't be queſtion'd by the very Bigots of the Cauſe, unleſs they intend to doubt of the Author's Prudence too; who, without doubt, is a perſon of as politick a Head, as ever brooded on the Elements of Treaſon, or hatch't a Rebellion: And if not at preſent reſtrain'd, more by ſome State-maxims, than Loyal Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; <hi>could raiſe a more formidable one, than the late Covenanting Banditi, diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at</hi> Boſworth-Bridge; So that in the very ſeaſonable Contrivance of it, it Parallels the ingenuity of the old Rebellious <hi>Scot,</hi> who drew up theirs in as convenient a Seaſon; when the Nation ſeem'd Unanimous enough to Rebel, without drawing up of a formal League of Gueranty, of cheating poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Souls into the miſerable neceſſity of fighting againſt their Prince, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perjur'd for him: But this mutual Agreement was thought then moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual to ſecure their Deſigns, as if they had diſtruſted of not being Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors enough, unleſs their Treaſons were divulg'd with a publick <hi>Manifeſto;</hi> and a ſort of <hi>Noverint <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi;</hi> or that the Conſpiracy would have look'd more Black and Helliſh, by being acted under-board, and in the dark.</p>
            <p>Whoever was the bold Contriver of this <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> certainly had no intent to let it lie long in a <hi>Cloſet,</hi> only to keep the <hi>Rats,</hi> and <hi>Mice</hi> from falling out; or perſuade them to a Union againſt their common Enemies, the <hi>Cats,</hi> and
<hi>Weaſels;</hi> the purport of the thing ſhews the intent, that it was to be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated; and to ſuch a Party too, as by their own confidence they boaſt the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt, and moſt numerous; which if it were really ſo, their licentiouſneſs is ſuch, that I am apt to believe, inſtead of keeping it in <hi>Cloſets,</hi> ſome of them would have got it read at
<hi>Croſſes,</hi> and <hi>Market-places;</hi> proclaim'd it like ſome
<hi>Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomew Show,</hi> and with Drums and Trumpets gull'd the ſilly Rout into Rebellion, as faſt as the Fools uſe to croud into the Booth: But 'tis ſhrowdly to be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, they are aw'd ſtill into good manners, and civility. Sure, otherwiſe, it were but a panick fear, ſo much to dread thoſe <hi>Guards,</hi> could they make ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>They would not be look't on with ſuch <hi>Terrour,</hi> and
<hi>Amazement,</hi> as is expreſs'd in their <hi>Oath;</hi> if they would but ſuffer theſe <hi>Frogs</hi> to fill the King's Chambers, with their harſh and diſcontented Murmurings, as they did the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> once, with their Croakings: Theſe little Democraticks, the ſcum of thoſe beggarly Elements, Mud, and Water; ſtill as mean as the one, and reſtleſs as the other; and with their <hi>Brethren</hi> in the Apologue, preſently Petitioning their <hi>Jupiters</hi> for a new King, as ſoon as weary of the old<hi>:</hi> Could theſe timerous Rats but get theſe dreadful
<hi>Guards,</hi> truly to repreſent <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s <hi>Puſs,</hi> and be really hung up by the Gaunches, we ſhould have them ſoon grow as bold as
<hi>Poll-Cats,</hi> and quickly divide the ſpoil of the King's Houſes; and ſure our <hi>Provident Patriot</hi> would never have exhorted the Subſcribers to his Covenant, to disband thoſe mercenary Forces, could they have march'd into <hi>White-hall,</hi> with a <hi>Nemine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicente;</hi> and have Rebelled without blows or knock: But ſure his Majeſty has Friends, and Forces enough to defend him, beſides thoſe that he pays for his preſervation: The ſtrongeſt <hi>Guards</hi> he has at preſent, are the faithful Hearts of his Honeſt Subjects, harden'd into Loyalty, by the miſeries they ſuffer'd for it; with Arms ſteel'd againſt the Piſtols and Blunderbuſſes of any new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels; having ſo lately been prov'd in the blood of the old; and why then muſt a Thouſand Men, or a handful of
<hi>Guards,</hi> frighten ſo many Millions; block up one of the moſt popular Cities in the World; hinder the reſolute Rabble from poſting into Rebellion, and riding Tantivy to the Devil?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97305:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Now to ſatisfie any one that our
<hi>Engliſh</hi> here, are as well Vers'd in the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Arts of drawing up Leagues and Covenants, as the <hi>Scot,</hi> that univerſal ill in the North; and proverbially wicked heretofore; let him but conſult thoſe Compendious ways our Gentlemen here took to promote their Rebellion, and he will find, that they drew up ſeveral Oaths, and Covenants, one of which was agreed on, and ſubſcribed by a long Liſt of Members, the ſixth of <hi>June,</hi> 43. before the <hi>Scotch Solemn League</hi> came over into <hi>England;</hi> which was not taken by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament here till the twenty fifth of
<hi>September</hi> following: This firſt that they agreed to, was an Inſtrument, that would have cut through all Government, and Monarchy; and his Majeſty's Head off too, without ſeconding the blow with another Engine, bought in the North. It was an agreement to Rebel una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly, to diſpenſe with all the old Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy to their King only, by ramming down new ones to fight againſt him: But yet as if they had diſtruſted an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Engagement, and their own <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants</hi> not bold and rebellious enough, to carry on their deſigns; Meſſengers are diſpatch't into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to fetch the draught of their <hi>Solemn League</hi> for a better Specimen; and to Complement the <hi>Scot</hi> into a Rebellion, which he had ſhewn himſelf ready enough to embrace; and to ſhew their own readineſs to ſwallow any thing that look't like a Combination againſt Monarchy; down goes the ſame
<hi>Solemn League</hi> with our Parliament here, which had been drawn up and Subſcrib'd by the <hi>Scots</hi> there: And now both Nations are agreed, and have very ſolemnly Sworn the Deſtruction of one unhappy <hi>Monarch:</hi> And no doubt, rather than the proſperity of the King's affairs ſhould have obſtructed the deep Deſigns of our Rebellious Senate, to ſubvert the Government; ſome of the time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Members that were alarm'd with the noiſe of it, would have Voted an Embaſſy to the <hi>Turks,</hi> or
<hi>Tartars;</hi> invited <hi>Mahometans</hi> to their aſſiſtance, Sworn, and Subſcrib'd to the very <hi>Alcoran;</hi> otherwiſe, certainly they would never have ſubmitted to ſuch weak Conceſſions, to promiſe conformity to the <hi>Kirk,</hi> admit the <hi>Scot</hi> into the Kingdom, and let Forreigners ſhare in that plunder, and booty, which at firſt they had only deſign'd for themſelves.</p>
            <p>To ſuch extremities does the undertaking of one Villany oft reduce Men, that they are forc't many times to be wicked even beyond their intention, and with a prepoſterous ſort of the Politicks, to reſolve on thoſe Meaſures, which are partly deſtructive to their own Cauſe: I think we can't at preſent invert the proceedings of the late Times, and prove that the <hi>Scot</hi> is now likely to call upon us for our late
<hi>Aſſociation,</hi> as we did heretofore on them for their <hi>Solemn League;</hi> And much rather that the Loyalty of the preſent
<hi>Scotch-men</hi> ſhould prevent the making ſuch a dangerous Trope, and fatal Inverſion; then that their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocal affection to our late Covenant ſhould give occaſion for it. But though their kindneſs to the Government hath of late been thus eminently manifeſted in their laſt Parliament, yet it is only of thoſe that are moſt eminent among them: And this our Male-contents here, can make uſe of, both as an argument to ſtrengthen their Cauſe, as well as to ſhake the Buttereſs of our own, and with an ingenious ſort of Sophiſtry, pervert the argument of their Opponents, to their own advantage: They know, though no hands can be found to their
<hi>Aſſociation</hi> in the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Scotland;</hi> yet they can be met with in a <hi>Field-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle;</hi> and though the
<hi>Teſt</hi> has been by many ſwallowed without ſo much as a Grimace, yet there are as many that have made very ſower Faces at it; ſome ſqueamiſh ſtomachs quite refuſed it; ſome made an Explanation of it, before it came to their mouths; others after it was in their Bellies; and ſome to Droll off the Authority of the Impoſers, and ridicule the
<hi>Oath,</hi> are ſaid to have tender'd it to their <hi>Dogs,</hi> and hang'd the <hi>Curs</hi> for refuſing it; witty waggs, no doubt, and ſuch as can give the World a Specimen of their parts, by being <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious</hi> Traytors; theſe are their politick ſurmiſes, and preſumptions, upon which, for all this, they build great expectation from the <hi>North;</hi> which I hope, though they may ſerve to animate the Party, will never be ſufficient to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then it, prove but the ſlender Twiggs of ſlight Argumentation, and ſuch as none but bare hope, and a ſinking Cauſe would take hold of.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97305:5"/>The firſt Factious Union we read of, that was made uſe of to reſiſt any Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority, was that in the year 1638; when the young Embryo of a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> was firſt hatch't in
<hi>Scotland</hi> about <hi>Glaſcow,</hi> and which ſerv'd for a Type and Copy to thoſe ſeveral, that have ſince follow'd; This Primitive one was agreed to, in oppoſition to the <hi>King</hi>'s Proclamation, for the diſperſing of the dangerous Rabble; but his Majeſties Security was then dreaded, even by thoſe that declar'd ſo much for his
<hi>Preſervation;</hi> and ſtraight in defiance of the <hi>King</hi>'s Commands, they read their <hi>own</hi> Proteſtations, made by the Lord
<hi>Hume,</hi> and Lord <hi>Lindſey,</hi> and others of ſeveral degrees, and quality; which they publiſh'd ſtraight, at <hi>Lithgow</hi> and other places, as <hi>Edenburgh;</hi> and to ſhew how much they dar'd Authority, they made the Heralds that came to ſee the Commands of their King
<hi>Obeyed,</hi> ſtay to ſee them very formally <hi>contradicted,</hi> and
<hi>expoſed:</hi> And it was high time then to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite,</hi> for the Juſtification of thoſe Villanies, which nought but <hi>Impudence</hi> and a
<hi>Combination</hi> could defend; And I have ſtill obſerv'd, that they all along drew up theſe Inſtruments, according as they grew more, and more Rebellious, making them perfect <hi>Leagues</hi> of <hi>Guaranty;</hi> to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves like Out-laws, and a ſort of <hi>Engliſh Banditi,</hi> from the puniſhments that the Statutes of Treaſon would have inflicted: And I am ſorry to find that our <hi>Aſſociators</hi> already fly to theſe Extremities, to which none of the late Rebels came, till they had made a further progreſs; and this bold leap ſhrouldly inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates, that they have proceeded further then the Nation is aware of, and that they are conſcious of more Treaſon, than is yet diſcover'd.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the occaſions of drawing up their <hi>firſt Covenant</hi> in <hi>Scotland;</hi> which was preach't up at <hi>Glaſcow</hi> to be Chriſt's Contract; and the people deſir'd to be hand-faſted to him, by ſhaking hands with it, by one <hi>Cant</hi> a zealous igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Bigot, that pretended himſelf an Ambaſſador from Heaven; though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed onely that of Sir <hi>Henry Wottons, ſent abroad to lye for the Publique.</hi> And thus we ſee ſuch Zealots are forc'd to make one ſin ſubſervient to another, and Blaſphemy a Pander to Rebellion. The correſpondency that there is between this <hi>Old Combination,</hi> and our late <hi>new One,</hi> is obſervable in this; that the one was to juſtifie a Proteſtation againſt the King's Pleaſure for diſperſing the Rabble, and dangerous Multitude; the other to contradict his Will in the legal Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Brother; And thus in ſome ſenſe it agrees with the very <hi>Primitive <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> my endeavours ſhall be to ſhow its agreement with all the reſt, and of which, in truth, our <hi>Aſſociation</hi> ſeems a choice ſort of Epitome; And I don't doubt but its Author had a collection of them on his Desk, for his better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: and thought his Subject very juſtiſiable, becauſe example for it; but that he has of the depoſing the King, and murdering of him too, if he has a mind to plead
<hi>Preſcription;</hi> and make Treaſonable Practices like the legal Proceedings in Parliament, warrantable by <hi>Preſidents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An <hi>Engliſh</hi> Oath and Covenant, comes out on the
6<hi>th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 43. and ſeem'd the effect of the
<hi>Cities</hi> importunity; <hi>His Majesties Loyal City;</hi> yet I think ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome call'd ſo, but in ſome <hi>Appeal from the Countrey,</hi> or in the head of their own <hi>Petitions.</hi> The Citizens promiſe the Loan of Forty Thouſand Pound de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Parliament, upon condition an <hi>Holy League</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd on the whole Kingdom; <hi>A great ſumm for the purchaſe of their own Slavery, but a ſmall price for the Head of a King;</hi> To pleaſe this <hi>City</hi> (that <hi>Bedlam</hi> of deluded Fools and Mad-men, gull'd always with the ſpecious names of
<hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> and as yet not wiſe enough to ſee even through a tranſparent Fallacy, and experienc'd Cheat;) to pleaſe theſe peeviſh Ideots, they have their humor, an the Parliament the money; out comes an <hi>Oath</hi> ſubſcribed by a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Worthy Members, and the ſcandalous Roll to be fill'd up by the Gentlemen of the Shop and Yard, many of which afterward ſerv'd a longer Apprentiſhip, in the bloody Rebellion, than e're they did in their own Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Employment.</p>
            <p>About the 24<hi>th</hi> of <hi>August,</hi> 43. The <hi>Scots</hi> being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ickl'd with the promiſes of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Committee that was ſent thither with an unlimitted Commiſſion, and ordered to cloſe with them upon any Conditions; firſt put out a Declaration<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97305:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>to publiſh their intentions of aſſiſting their Friends, the Parliament in <hi>England;</hi> and ſo the bargain is ſtruck for rooting out Monarchy and Epiſcopacy, and the King ſold before he came to their hands; and ſtrait all that were not incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated either by Youth, or Old Age, all from Sixteen to Sixty that could but lift an hand againſt their Soveraign, are muſter'd up for the march: And then to ſecure to themſelves the promiſes of their Chapmen, which were no leſs then a ſhare in all the Revenues of the Church; the cunning Merchants, inſtead of <hi>Bond</hi> and <hi>Obligation,</hi> the common ties in ordinary Traffick, invent a new ſort of ſecurity by
<hi>ſolemn League and Covenant;</hi> which was preſently ſent over to their State-jobbers at <hi>Weſtminster,</hi> on the 31 of the ſame Month; and on the 25<hi>th</hi> of <hi>September</hi> following was by them ſubſcrib'd in St. <hi>Margarets</hi> Church; a moſt improper place for ratifying ſuch a bloody <hi>Covenant,</hi> a Contract which Heaven it ſelf could never ſanctifie, and which for its lying and hypocriſie, ſeem'd the very draught of Hell. Now the method I ſhall take, ſhall be to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel our diſcover'd <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> both with this <hi>Holy League</hi> that was drawn up by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the <hi>ſolemn One</hi> that was afterward ſent them by the <hi>Scots,</hi> and upon the comparing of the ſeveral Paragraphs digreſs a little into ſome needful Animadverſion; but for a little while ſtill continue ſome general Obſervations.</p>
            <p>Theſe Treaſonable Bonds and Obligations our old Rebels bound themſelves in, that ſo they might both be ſecure of one another; and Rebel with a ſort of <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Manifesto,</hi> and no perſon queſtion the notoriouſneſs of that Fact, which by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo publiquely divulg'd, and impudently own'd, was made a little famous; and this, no doubt, made Mr.
<hi>Nye</hi> to give it ſuch an Elogy; but not content to impoſe on the frailty, onely of a few credulous <hi>Mortals,</hi> they endeavour to abuſe even <hi>Omniſcience</hi> it ſelf; entitle <hi>Heaven</hi> to thoſe Villanies, which nought but the depth of <hi>Hell</hi> could contrive; call that their Rebellious <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> an <hi>Holy League,</hi> &amp; make their own abominable Cauſe, that of the <hi>Almightie's;</hi> certainly theſe Men that declar'd ſo much for Religion, could hardly be ſuppos'd to know their Bibles; where they might ſoon have found God's diſlike of ſuch proceedings, where <hi>Rebellion</hi> is made worſe then the ſin of
<hi>Witchcraft;</hi> and altogether as much an Imp of Hell and the Devil; but the profane madneſs of Zealots is ſuch, that they can imagine even the Deity concern'd above, for the Seditious Murmurings of the Rabble below: and that when ever their Vicegerents are complain'd of by the Faction; they are ſtrait by the King of Kings for their ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, depos'd; <hi>And God will make the Sons of Princes bow down unto ye; the greatest that have afflicted and deſpiſed ye, ſhall lye at your fect.</hi> Heyrick <hi>to the Commons, May</hi> 27. 46. <hi>p.</hi> 31. The natural horror, and deteſtation, I have always had of theſe late proceedings, though onely acquainted with their Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, has oft made me thank my God, that I had no being in this World, when it was arriv'd to ſuch an Inſuperable wickedneſs; when Vice ſeem'd to have fix'd her Pillars here in this Iſle, and made it ſin almoſt to a <hi>Non ultra;</hi> the kind breath that I firſt drew was with a reſtor'd Peace, and a recall'd Soveraign, and with both thoſe I hope it will expire too; And this juſt reſentment, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable paſſion againſt ſuch villainous Practices, will oft tranſport me into ſome digreſſion; the deſign being only to make a compariſon, between thoſe two <hi>Old Covenants,</hi> and our late <hi>New One;</hi> but if the Parallels are not ſo Mathematical, or the Lines obſerve no ſuch Geometrick diſtance; any deflexion will be very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, when the very hand trembles that draws them.</p>
            <p>But to go to the Compariſon, though our late
<hi>Aſſociation</hi> does not carry in its impudent Front an impious Name too, though <hi>Holy League</hi> now be none of the Sanctified Title for
<hi>Rebellion,</hi> yet the effects of it may be as dangerous and the intent as full of Treaſon; neither would it have been a piece of Policy or even common Prudence in the Contrivers, to have call'd it either <hi>League</hi> or
<hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> for thoſe very people that would have applauded the deſign, might have diſlik'd ſuch an Appellation; And many that are ready enough to engage in a Treaſon, would be loath to have a <hi>T</hi> burnt in their Fore-head; <hi>Aſſociation</hi> will be eaſily ſwallow'd, when
<hi>League</hi> might ſtick a little in the Throat. The diſtinguiſhing Streamers of <hi>Blew</hi> and <hi>Green</hi> Ribband at preſent take mightily,<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97305:6"/>though the bloody colours of a Parliament Army, would not be preſently ſo pleaſant a ſpectacle.</p>
            <p>But yet here there is almoſt an Identity of practice; the Almighty is moſt ſolemnly invok't in the beginning of the <hi>Oath;</hi> Priviledges of Parliament; Laws of the Kingdom; Liberties of the Subject; Popery; Proteſtant Religion; all the ſame numerical pretenſions, the ſame Words, Expreſſions, and Out-crys; and what can be the conſequence, but that the ſame <hi>Rebellion</hi> will follow too? When that <hi>Holy League</hi> was bought by the <hi>City</hi> in forty three, at forty thouſand pound; when the <hi>Citizens</hi> had been the Parliaments Chapmen, it was thought fit they ſhould be their Factors too; and in order thereunto, they were hired to put off thoſe groſs Commodities, of Mutiny, Petitioning, Beſieging of <hi>Weſt-minſter,</hi> and <hi>White-hall,</hi> railing at the King, abuſing of his Council; bawling for Juſtice, with Noiſe, Tumult, and Inſurrection, and all the confus'd repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of a wild, and diſtracted people: Such Factious drudgery being moſt proper to be carried on, by thoſe <hi>Tylers, Straws,</hi> and <hi>Maſinelloes;</hi> unbecoming the gravity of a Senate, that ſate brooding on the pure Elements of Treaſon; drawing out the Schemes, and Plat-forms of a Common-wealth; and being too certain in their State-Aſtrology, calculated the future ruine of Three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms: Circumſtances, I fancy, were much the ſame, when this Modern <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> with Oath and Obligation was firſt contrived; which
'tis very probable was drawn up by ſome politick Head, that knew what Influence it would have on the Juncture of affairs; no doubt 'twas firſt hatch't when the laſt Parliament ſate at <hi>London,</hi> when the Licentiouſneſs of the <hi>City</hi> was ſuch, as nothing but the Tumults in the late Times could exceed it; and perhaps nothing but an Act, and fear of Puniſhment, obſtructed the concourſe of the Rabble, with their
<hi>Old</hi> way of Petitioning with Blunderbuſſes, Pikes, and Staves.
<hi>White-hall</hi> was then often times block't up with this Armed Rout, when their Leagues and Covenants were on the Anvil; <hi>And we have thoſe now, that when this Aſſociation was a ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering, could threaten to pull the black Man out of it.</hi> Diſſenting Proteſtants were then to be favoured, and conniv'd at; <hi>And now the Laws to be Repealed for exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them from puniſhment.</hi> The King then declar'd a favourer of Popery;
<hi>Now ſuſpected ready to introduce it.</hi> The Queen then traduc'd for a Plot on the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>And now aſpers'd with the ſame Accuſation.</hi> His Majeſties Friends paſt for Evil Counſellors; <hi>And now Betrayers of the Liberties of the Subject.</hi> Judges and Privy Counſellors were then impeach't; <hi>And I think ſome of them meet with the ſame dealing at preſent.</hi> The proceedings in Eccleſiaſtical Courts were then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd; <hi>Now taken into conſideration. Montague, Manwaring</hi> Clergy-men ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; Thompſon <hi>and others taken into cuſtody.</hi> The King to have no Money till Grievances were redreſſed; <hi>None now till the Bill of Excluſion is paſt.</hi> Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous Petitioning then encouraged and promoted; <hi>Now, a Proclamation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it to be examin'd, and the adviſers puniſh'd. Arbitrary Power</hi> then the ſole cry; <hi>Now the doleful burden of the Song.</hi> This was the ſtate of Affairs, when their
<hi>Leagues</hi> were a making; <hi>This our Condition now the</hi> Aſſociation <hi>is a Foot:</hi> All the difference is, the <hi>King</hi> is not yet driven out of his <hi>Palace;</hi> nor a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Army</hi> yet in the <hi>Field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having Parallel'd the Circumſtances of Time and Affairs, when theſe <hi>Engines</hi> of Rebellion were ſet a work; we will fall a comparing theſe <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of the Devil themſelves.</p>
            <p>The Introduction to the <hi>Solemn League</hi> and
<hi>Covenant,</hi> begins in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner;
<note place="margin">Solemn League.</note>
               <hi>We Barons, Knights, and Burgeſſes;</hi> And in the ſame words the Contriver Uſhers in his
<hi>Aſſociation;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aſſociat.</note>
               <hi>We Knights, Burgeſſes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But one would think this Verbal tranſcription might have been civilly ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, till theſe <hi>Knights</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> had ſhaken off all their Allegiance to their Prince; and been upon the ſame terms with the King, that they were when they called in the <hi>Scot,</hi> and took the <hi>Covenant,</hi> that was cut and dried for them in the
<hi>North.</hi> I fancy, were the rude Animal that Penn'd it, known to the Lower<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97305:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Houſe, he would have but little thanks for complementing them with the firſt place in his Paper; and placing ſo many worthy perſons in the higheſt rank of his Treaſon, as if they were to be as Eminent for that, as they are for their Love and Service to their Countrey; why had it not better, and more civilly, begun without naming any body? Or, if there muſt needs have been ſome Head to this Rebellious Monſter; the word
<hi>Citizens,</hi> might have ſerv'd to compleat this prodigy of intended Treaſon; I am ſure this Inſtrument ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes more the ſenſe and clamour of their mighty <hi>Babylon,</hi> than of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<hi>Repreſentatives:</hi> And then why not, <hi>We Mayor, Aldermen</hi> and
<hi>Sheriffs,</hi> as well as <hi>Barons, Knights,</hi> and
<hi>Burgeſſes;</hi> But he proceeds very methodically, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the true Standard of all <hi>Leagues,</hi> and <hi>Covenants.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Aſſociat.</note>
               <hi>Finding to the grief of our Hearts, the Popiſh Prieſt, and Jeſuits, with the Papiſts and their Adherents, and Abettors; have for ſeveral years purſued a moſt Pernicious and Helliſh Plot; to Root out the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, to Subvert our Laws, and Liberties,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Holy League, <hi>June</hi> 6.
43.</note>
               <hi>Whereas there hath been, and now is in this Kingdom, a Popiſh and Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Plot; for the Subverſion of the True Proteſtant Reform'd Religion, and Liberty of the Subject,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <p>That there is a Popiſh Plot now, is the advantage this
<hi>Aſſociator</hi> has above him that contriv'd the Form of that on the Sixth of <hi>June;</hi> and ſo has the opportunity of telling <hi>Truth,</hi> when the other was forc'd to <hi>Ly</hi> for it: There was no <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> then that was ever diſcover'd by the moſt induſtrious Bigot of the Cauſe, or even appear'd by the moſt partial Hiſtorian to their ſide; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps there was no <hi>Salamanca</hi> Doctors in thoſe dayes, that could out-witt, and trepan the Subtil Jeſuite: But methinks if there were any Record extant, it might be found in the careful Collections of Mr.
<hi>Ruſhworth;</hi> who never omitted inſerting the leaſt ſcrap of Parchment, that could ſerve for his purpoſe: indeed he gives a Specimen of a Letter, found upon the taking ſome Jeſuites at <hi>Clerken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well;</hi> how far that may prove a Plot upon the Nation, I ſubmit to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Reader. However we ſee that the Outcry was then as great upon
<hi>Preſumption;</hi> as now upon <hi>Proof:</hi> and Popiſh Plot, Popiſh Army, Popiſh Council, Popiſh Prelate, was the Burden of all their
<hi>Oaths,</hi> and <hi>Covenants;</hi> the Bug-bears to fright the Childiſh Rabble, from their Reſpect to the <hi>Crown,</hi> and Reverence to the Church. And had they not at preſent a <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> a Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor for their own; 'tis ſhrewdly to be ſuſpected they would not long be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, but tranſcribe the Politicks of their Fore-fathers, make up with
<hi>Fiction</hi> what is wanting in <hi>Diſcovery;</hi> hatcht thoſe Eggs of Plot and Conſpiracy, in ſome Oven, or Dunghill; which Truth and Nature were never like to bring to any maturity; and therefore certainly it is the intereſt of our Church to cry down <hi>Popery,</hi> more than of thoſe that diſſent from it, becauſe whilſt it ſtill ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts ours, it can help to eſtabliſh theirs, ſo that imagining people in their <hi>Wits</hi> we muſt ſuppoſe them promoting of their <hi>Intereſt</hi> too, and then this conſequence will naturally follow, That the Church of <hi>England,</hi> really deſerts that of <hi>Rome,</hi> whilſt the Diſſenters do but pretend it; now in the next Paragraph the <hi>Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciator</hi> falls aboard the <hi>Duke;</hi> who muſt ſuſtain a full Broad-ſide of accuſation, and all the whole ſtock of Argument, but I have heard of a fellow that ſhot at a Deer, but killed the King, and you ſhall ſee what a by-blow he gives His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Aſſociat.</note>
               <hi>And it being notorious, That they have been highly encourag'd by</hi> J. D. <hi>of</hi> Y. <hi>who hath ſo far prevailed, that he hath created many and great dependants upon him, by beſtowing Offices of Preferment both in Church and State,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <p>So this is good and ſerves the turn moſt admirably; the
<hi>Duke</hi> is a Papiſt, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns the King; gets in Popiſh Officers, and then the tranſition is very rational<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97305:7"/>to prove the
<hi>King</hi> Popiſhly affected that hearkens to him. But ſure this bad Logick was never intended to be impos'd on the Nation, to be receiv'd as Goſpel, ſworn too and vow'd, as well as their <hi>Covenant</hi> in Baptiſm; I thought the danger of the <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor</hi> had been ſuch, that there was nothing left to mind beſide: but this
<hi>Aſſociator</hi> ſeems to be of the opinion of a late
<note n="*" place="margin">Anſwer to the Kings De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.</note> Politician, who thinks the Duke more dangerous, as a <hi>Minister</hi> of State, than <hi>Heir</hi> of the Crown; If ſo, why will the removing of him from the Kings Ear not ſatisfie theſe diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented men? certainly in reaſon there ought to be no more clamor, and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, when the Matter and Object of both is removed; and if the preſiding at the Helm, and diſpoſing of Church and State Affairs be ſuch a Grievance, then tis no wonder there has been ſuch continual Out-cryes, againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> and no doubt in a ſhort time will be raiſed too againſt the <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners</hi> in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs. But then what can be the reſult of this to ſober thoughts, but that all this ſtir is made, either by thoſe that have a mind to have ſome ſhare in the preferring of others, or would needs be preferred to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what themſelves? And then all the clamorous Accuſations here againſt his Highneſs, inſinuate that ſomething muſt be ſpeedily done againſt him, and his <hi>Adherents:</hi> ſo then it ſeems the Gentleman thinks like other people, that tis a chance but the <hi>King</hi> may ſurvive his
<hi>Brother,</hi> therefore tis fit to begin preſently, leſt the pretence for Rebellion, ſhould be ſuperſeded by his untimely end; thus theſe Sycophants hugg the Caſe of the <hi>Duke,</hi> as they do their darling the
<hi>Plot;</hi> and wiſh him no more out of the way, than they do their
<hi>E.</hi> of <hi>S.</hi> the want of the one, would take away the pretence for their Combination; the other a Patriot. I muſt confeſs, as to this particular Caſe of the <hi>Duke,</hi> the Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel can't be ſo exactly drawn with old <hi>Leagues</hi> and <hi>Covenants,</hi> becauſe they had then no ſuch unhappy Prince that could ſerve to palliate their intended Rebellion; and it can't be expected it ſhould agree with them in all particulars; when this preſaging <hi>Comet</hi> of a War appears now ſo many years ſince, though unhappily on the ſame <hi>Horizon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by what I can obſerve from the Hiſtory of thoſe times, a
<hi>Duke</hi> was then the burden of the ſong; It ſeems to me a diſputable Problem, whether the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Buckingham</hi>'s fall by that Villanious Aſſaſſin, did not prevent his dying a glorious Martyr for his <hi>Prince,</hi> &amp; a Sacrifice to the Vengeance of the people; though even that unexpected end and private Murder, may ſerve to inroll him in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrology, as well as thoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that were afterward more <hi>publickly</hi> executed by the bloody Senate. For it appear'd by the confeſſion of the zealous murderer, that he rather eſpous'd the Nations Cauſe than his own;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Ruſhw.</note> that he look't on the <hi>Duke</hi> as an evil inſtrument in the Common-wealth; and why ſo? becauſe he was convinc'd of it by the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> in Parliament: And if that will preſently make the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon impeach't an <hi>Out-law,</hi> brand him like a <hi>Cain,</hi> to be kill'd by every one he meets, as this murderous Villain ſeems to ſuggeſt in his bold Attempt; Then I pitty thoſe unfortunate Gentlemen that are expos'd by the late Votes, as Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to their King and Countrey, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> as perſons that may be purſued like Wolves, and worried with Dogs; and take it for a kindneſs to be throughly diſpatch't, ſuffer but a ſingle death, by the generous hand of ſome friendly <hi>Felton.</hi> That Parliament in the late times, whoſe Votes thus animated this Aſſaſſin, you ſee had a <hi>Duke</hi> too, whom they thought too near the King's Ear, and Heart, and though they did not draw up a <hi>Covenant</hi> againſt <hi>him,</hi> as this
<hi>Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciator</hi> has againſt <hi>ours,</hi> yet the Clamor of the Commons at that time, was the ſame with this <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> and that even to a word, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I.
<q rend="inline">
                     <hi>That he had ſo far prevailed as to create many and great Dependants upon him,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </item>
               <item>II.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Aſſociat.</note>
                  <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>That notwithſtanding all the continual endeavours of the Parliament, to deliver His Majeſty from his Councils, and out of the power of the ſaid Duke; yet he has been ſo prevalent that Parliaments have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonably Prorogued and Diſſolved, when in hot purſuit of ill Miniſters.</hi>
                  </q>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97305:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>This was exactly the fearful out-cry, againſt the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> the <hi>praelude</hi> to the War that enſued; and that is Verbatim the bold <hi>Aſſociators</hi> Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the Duke of <hi>York:</hi> And very probably the
<hi>Signal</hi> to the Rebellion he intends.</p>
            <p>To proceed now to Parallel the reſt of the Paragraphs in the Preface to that Oath of <hi>Aſſociation.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Aſſociat.</note>
               <hi>And as we conſidering with heavy hearts, how greatly the Strength, Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and Treaſure of the Nation is waſted and conſumed, by the intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate expences, and management of theſe wicked deſtructive deſigns; and finding the ſame Councils ſtill purſued with the utmoſt divelliſh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and deſire of Revenge.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>And now pray mark the Original.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scoth.</hi> ſol. Leg.</note>
               <hi>And calling to mind the Conſpiracies, Attempts, Practiſes of the Enemies of God, and how much their Rage, Power, and Preſumption is of late, and at this time exerciſed and encreaſed; whereof the deplorable, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs'd and dangerous eſtate of this Kingdom, are preſent and publick Teſtimonies.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>What reaſon there was then of thoſe complaints, is beſt known to thoſe that made them; The ſtate of the Kingdom was <hi>dangerous, diſtreſs'd, deplorable.</hi> And I'l give them leave to deſcribe it, in the moſt miſerable terms, that a tongue full of grief can expreſs, or a diſturb'd Soul conceive, and ſhall ſympathiſe very much with them in their Lamentations; But tell them, that in theſe Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical bewailings of their Countrey, they much blazon their own cruelties towards it; And ſhall ſhew how I apprehend the Nation came to fall into that lamentable condition. Its State began to be <hi>dangerous</hi> aſſoon as the City to be diſcontented; 'twas <hi>diſtreſſed</hi> when the <hi>King</hi> was forc't to borrow money upon Loan; 'twas moſt <hi>deplorable</hi> when he was neceſſitated to take up Arms for his Life, and at laſt with ſo much ignominy to loſe it too. But why this <hi>Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> ſhould ſing this ſorrowful Ditty, and think the preſent times ſo deplorable, is not quite ſo intelligible; unleſs he is conſcious of his having contributed much towards their being ſo, and this peeviſh complainer ſomewhat of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of thoſe Mad-men who have almoſt an abſtracted Idaea of thoſe things they rave for, imagine thoſe Phrenſies the real Objects of their <hi>deluded</hi> Opticks, which in truth are onely of their
<hi>distemper'd Intellectuals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Poor tender heart! how it grieves him to conſider, the
<hi>Reputation, Strength, Treaſure</hi> of the Nation, ſo miſerably
<hi>waſted</hi> and <hi>conſumed;</hi> and in kind compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to his diſtreſſed Countrey, has thought on a Soveraign remedy to cloſe its wounds, and unite the pieces of a broken-hearted, dejected, and diſaffected People; a preſcription much like thoſe of our late Quacking Divines; the Soul's <hi>Balm of Gilead;</hi> the <hi>Salve</hi> and <hi>Ointment</hi> for a bruiſed <hi>Conſcience:</hi> And now we have got ſome cloſing, healing Balſam of <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> for the uniting of all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united Proteſtants; But I am afraid ſuch Unctions as theſe, will produce the ſame Symptoms that the Fat and Greaſe does in a Chandler's Shop; make the little Tenement the more ready to catch at every ſpark, and break out the ſooner into flame: And firſt this Honourable Perſon, (for certainly he is no ſmall Man amongſt the Faction) is mightily concerned for the
<hi>Reputation</hi> of the Nation; when 'twas a <hi>Covenant</hi> that made it ſcandalous, even to the Rebellious <hi>Dutch;</hi> and made our old
<hi>Albion</hi> look like a pitiful Colony in <hi>New England;</hi> full of Quakers, Anabaptiſts, and all the wild diſtraction of Schiſm and Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; the decay of its <hi>ſtrength</hi> ſhivers him into quaking Fits, and diſmal appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of being knock't on the Head by the
<hi>French;</hi> when all this while not one mite muſt be contributed for the getting ſo much as a Cudgel-butt to ward the blow; I fancy this Gentleman eſpouſes the Maxims of the late Political Caſuiſt<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97305:8"/>at
<hi>Malmsbury,</hi> who has laid it down as a principle, that Subjects owe no longer obedience to their <hi>Prince,</hi> than he has ſtrength and ability to defend them: If ſo, 'tis no wonder the Treaſury is ſo poor, and the ſtrength of the Nation ſo much decay'd; as in ſpight of all reaſon to the contrary, our <hi>Aſſociator</hi> is willing ſhould ſtill be ſo; for 'twould be but madneſs in him, and a breaking of his own meaſures, to wiſh the King any Money, or in a condition to protect his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; for that would remove thoſe diſpenſations he would have to warrant his diſobedience, and then he muſt rebel without a Licenſe: But certainly this is not only <hi>Tranſcribing</hi> of the Politicks of Mr. <hi>Hobs,</hi> but <hi>Improving</hi> of them too; ſhews him not only ready to diſpenſe with his Allegiance to the King, whenever his Exchequer is low; but very willing it ſhould always be ſo; and then upon that account not barely to withdraw his obedience, but very fairly draws up a Covenant for Rebellion; and ſo puts in for another poſition, of that Eminent Philoſopher, <hi>A ſtate of War:</hi> But yet give me leave to inform this ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<hi>Aſſociator,</hi> and with as merry a heart as he pretends his to be heavy; that this his conſidering Cap, is not rightly plac't on his factious Noddle; and though he conſiders the <hi>Strength, Treaſure,</hi> and
<hi>Reputation</hi> of the Nation ſo much Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and Conſum'd, I apprehend no ſuch thing at all, but rather the quite contrary.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Were our <hi>Reputation</hi> ſo low with our Neighbours, as to make them think us a Bankrupt Kingdom; a Parcel of poor Raſcals, forc't to cheat our Creditors, and compound for Bread; as this honeſt Patriot kindly fancies his Countrey to be; I can't ſee why our Trade and Traſſick; and that almoſt with the whole World too, ſhould continue ſtill interrupted, and without the leaſt danger of being impeded; I know the Actions of the ſeveral Companies, riſe and fall, upon the ſeveral emergencies of new affairs: But certainly, the Credit and Reputation of the Kingdom, no way depends on thoſe viciſſitudes; yet I grant there is a great noiſe of a certain great City's growing poor; but I think it would be happier for a certain King that lives near it, were it leſs wealthy; it was
<hi>Jeſuran</hi>'s waxing Fat, that made him kick at God Almighty, and 'tis that, I believe, makes them to ſpurn at the Crown.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Were the <hi>Strength</hi> of the Kingdom ſo much decayed; ſo weak and contemptible, I can't imagine why our Aſſiſtance ſhould be deſired by our <hi>Neighbours,</hi> when not in a capacity to defend our <hi>ſelves:</hi> Sure the late <hi>League</hi> of
<hi>Guaranty</hi> was not then propoſed to our Nation, nor tender'd to the King of <hi>England,</hi> and his entrance deſir'd before all the Princes of the Empire, if we are look't upon as a people ſo weak and inconſiderable, and our King's Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Alliance not worth the ſeeking. Sure the Nation that has beat the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and fought the <hi>French</hi> with all his luſty Guard of <hi>Switzers,</hi> is not ſo ſuddenly dwindled into <hi>Pigmees,</hi> and only fit to ſight with <hi>Cranes;</hi> and perhaps this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociator and his Crew, may upon grapling find, that 'tis no ſuch eaſie matter to ſubdue thoſe <hi>Guards,</hi> he would ſo willingly remove; and that his Majeſty has too ſtout a Party of Cavaliers, to ſuffer a ſecond Plunder, and Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Though he ſuſpect the Treaſury to be at ſo low an Ebb; to have nothing viſible in it but dry Duſt, and barren Sand, and ſo to give occaſion for ſuch a ſeaſonable <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting</hi> againſt the Government; he may find himſelf much out in his Sounding; and that his Will, and good Wiſhes were the plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, inſtead of Reaſon and Deliberation; and that the Tide there, by his leave, is too high for him yet, to wade through into Rebellion; and now 'tis time to parallel another Paragraph.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Aſſociat.</note>
               <hi>We therefore endeavoured in a Parliamentary way to exclude the D. but finding the means utterly rejected; we thought fit to propoſe to all True Proteſtants, an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion amongst themſelves; by Solemn and Sacred pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of mutual aſſiſtance; and hold it our bounden Duty to joyn our ſelves in a Declaration, of our united affections, and reſolutions, in the Form enſuing.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97305:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scotch</hi> ſolemn League.</note>
               <hi>We have now at laſt after other means, of Supplication, Remonſtrances, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, and Sufferings, for the Preſervation of our ſelves, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, after mature deliberation reſolved and determin'd to enter into a Mutual and Solemn League and Covenant, which we all Subſcribe, and with our hands lifted up to the moſt high God,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Holy League, June 6. 43.</note>
               <hi>And finding that many ways of force and treachery are continually attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to bring to utter ruine and deſtruction, the Parliament; and that which is moſt dear unto us, the Proteſtant Religion; it is thought fit that all who are true hearted, and Lovers of their Countrey, ſhould bind themſelves each to other in a Sacred Vow.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Here the <hi>Aſſociator</hi> has ſhown himſelf a right ſiltching Plagiary, and not only Copied out the <hi>Senſe</hi> of his originals, but almoſt the very <hi>words,</hi> after many
<hi>Remonſtrances, Supplications, Proteſtations;</hi> after a
<hi>Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary way to exclude the Duke:</hi> He might as well have ſaid, Now there remains nothing to do but to drive the King out of his Palace, Proclaim all his followers Delinquents; all his <hi>adherents</hi> Enemies to King and Countrey; ſend poſt to <hi>Scotland,</hi> Meſſengers to the Field-Conventicles, get another Army from the North, ſwallow a <hi>ſecond Solemn League;</hi> and then we ſhall have exactly a <hi>ſecond</hi> 43. the perfect Revolution of a ſad <hi>Platonick</hi> Year, as well as a
<hi>Plato redivivus:</hi> But I hope the times will prove kinder to this
<hi>Aſſociator,</hi> than he willingly wou'd be to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: And though ſo reſolutely poſting to the Devil, he may meet with many a kind block in the way; ſuch a <hi>Covenant</hi> is ſooner drawn up than Subſcribed to; and more of Subſcriptions may be got than of Horſe, Men, and Arms to defend it; and though all the Villany ſhould ſucceed even to Rebellion, there is power enough left in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, they fancy ſo weak, to keep them from ſetting up again their Idol of a Common-wealth; and making the deluded people fall down and worſhip the Gods of their own hands. <hi>Finding our ſelves not able to exclude the Duke, we think fit &amp;c.</hi> He might as well have ſaid, Are reſolved to bring it about one way, or another: But how long hath it been a warrantable piece of Doctrine, to attempt that by foul means, which they deſpond of getting by fair? ſure the Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this can never be juſtified by the beſt of their Caſuiſts, neither Dr. <hi>O.</hi> nor Mr. <hi>B.</hi> will preach up this as ſound Doctrine; at preſent I don't know what might be done were <hi>Conſcience Liberty</hi> tolerated again, and one of them made the mouth or <hi>Prolocutor</hi> of an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: for 'tis obſervable that ſuch mens opinions proportionably widen with their Authority; and as ſoon as their dominion, which is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Grace, begins once to be enlarged by it too, they Commence La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinarian in Caſes of Conſcience, anſwerable to the extent of their Power and Government; and thus a fellow trots along, a pretty ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Republican, as long as the Law can bridle him, and make the Beaſt ſubmit to Monarchy; but grows a Deviliſh head-ſtrong Rebel, when once the Reins are got between his Teeth: And I believe only the thoughts of his having unhorſed his Rider, makes our
<hi>Aſſociator</hi> ſo bold as to kick at him too. But I hope he'll find there is Law e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough left to back him yet; and that there are Whips, Scourges, Axes, and Gibbets, notwithſtanding they are now grown no more terrible than
<hi>Bug-bears,</hi> and <hi>Scare-crows;</hi> as if only deſign'd to frighten
<hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97305:9"/>and <hi>Small-birds:</hi> And all this boldneſs infus'd into all ſorts of villains, with a Doſe of
<hi>Ignoramus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I don't ſee but upon the ſame grounds theſe following Proceedings may be very juſtifiable, and the Gentleman ſhall give me leave to inſert a Clauſe or two for him in his <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> which by negligence I fancy, and not want of good will were omitted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We therefore</hi> endeavor'd in a Parliamentary way to remove all evil Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors from the King; ſome of which were impeach't, (as alſo ſeveral of the <hi>Arbitrary Judges</hi>) of High-Treaſon; on purpoſe to bring them to condign Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. But theſe means of the King and Kingdoms ſafety being rejected, <hi>Ergo—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what then? muſt we therefore preſently ſwear, to draw the one out of the Council-Chamber by the Ears, and dragg the other out of
<hi>Westminſter-Hall</hi> to the Block? But here you ſhall have the Tenor of the Oath, and the Copies from which it was drawn.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Aſſociat.</note>
               <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>Do in the preſence of God, ſolemnly Vow, Promiſe and Proteſt, to maintain and defend, to the utmoſt of my power, with my perſon, and Eſtate, the true Proteſtant Religion, the Power and Priviledges of Parliament, the lawful Rights and Liberties of the Subject.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Scoth Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note>
               <hi>I</hi> A. B.
<hi>With hands lifted up to the moſt High God do ſwear, That I ſhall ſincerely, really, and conſtantly, endeavour the preſervation of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion in</hi> Scotland, &amp;c. <hi>That I will with the ſame ſincerity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>endeavour to preſerve the Rights and Priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Liberties of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Holy League.</note>
               <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>In the preſence of Almighty God, do declare Vow and Covenant, in order to the ſecurity, preſervation of the true Reformed Religion, and Liberties of the Subject,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <p>Certainly they muſt be the ſofteſt fools in the World, an eaſie ſort of Ideots, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the cunning of common brutes, that can be cheated with the ſame bait, whoſe diſguiſed hook they have already felt, and ſmarted by; I believe the contriver of this <hi>Oath,</hi> intended the impoſing it onely on Fools and Mad-men, or the <hi>City Mobile</hi> worſe than both; <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> may go down again with ſuch Aſses, who apprehend neither aright; ſuch as underſtand the ſenſe of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and their <hi>Geneva-Bibles</hi> though in
<hi>plain Engliſh,</hi> as much as they would the one in its <hi>antiquated French,</hi> and the other in its <hi>original Hebrew.</hi> But ſure no man in his Wits can imagine the wiſer part of the Nation, ſo ſoon deluded with a repeated fallacy: Tis obſervable when on the ſpecious pretences of
<hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> the Government of Church and State, were both ſubverted, the Magiſtracy triumph'd over by the Criminals and Rogues, it was to puniſh us, and the Church perſecuted by thoſe factious Diſſenters that were to be corrected by it, when the whole Kingdom at laſt was ſet in a Combuſtion, and nought at length but the Kings blood thought ſufficient to quench the flame; 'tis obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I ſay, that ſome of the trepan'd Nation began to reflect on the barbarouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuch horrid Proceedings; And to be ſurpriz'd with a ſort of horror at their own Progreſs; and being pinch't with the Quaere, Why they firſt engaged in ſuch deſigns? would ſtill anſwer that they ne'r intended it ſhould have come to that paſs; A poor excuſe and expiation for ſo much Guilt and Villany. But ſure ſuch Gentlemen, ought now to be very careful of putting to Sea again, that have been ſo dangerouſly toſt in the Storm; and not to be decoy'd out with the calm ſmilings of a ruddy Sky, and the ſlattering hopes of fair weather. But yet, 'tis but ſaying to ſome, the
<hi>Religion</hi> is again in danger, their <hi>Priviledges</hi> infring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97305:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>And we are for launching out again into the purple Waves, and another Red-Sea of Blood; drawing up <hi>Covenants</hi> again, abuſing the King, Libelling the Government, with <hi>Pen</hi> and
<hi>Paſquil,</hi> the next door to the reforming it with the <hi>Sword.</hi> But I hope the conſtitution of it is ſuch that it will not now be ſo eaſily ſubverted; like a well ſet bone, grown the ſtronger for its being broken; and like the Buildings of their great and mighty
<hi>Babylon,</hi> which are now the better ſecur'd againſt the wild ragings of a Fire, by their ſuffering ſo much in the rebellious Flame.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Aſſociat,</note>
               <hi>I will endeavour to reſiſt all encroachments of Arbitrary Power, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour entirely to Disband ſuch mercenary Forces as we have reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve were raiſed to advance it, and are ſtill kept up in and about the City of</hi> London,
<hi>to the great Amazement and Terror of all good People of the Land.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Scotch ſolemn League.</note>
               <hi>We ſhall with all faithfulneſs endeavour the ſuppreſſing of all ſuch as have been and ſhall be incendiaries, malignants, evil inſtruments, divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the King from his People.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder theſe they comprehended, as appear'd by their Proceedings afterward, all thoſe that stood up for the defence of their Soveraign; all thoſe Forces which for a while kept his Majeſty from the Block, were then look't on too as mercenary Switzers, hired to promote an Arbitrary Power.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Holy League.</note>
               <hi>I will not conſent to the laying down of Arms, ſo long as the Papiſts now in open War againſt the Parliament, ſhall by force of Arms be protected from the Juſtice thereof.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>And they might as well have call'd them <hi>Turks</hi> or
<hi>Tartars,</hi> for 'twas the intereſt onely of thoſe Rebels to fix the moſt opprobrious names on the Kings beſt Subjects. And Papiſt then was as odious an appellation, as malice could affix on the worſt of Enemies; And was as dreadful as our <hi>Aſſociators</hi> new Scare-Crow <hi>mercenary Forces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Terror of <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> I grant is dreadful enough to thoſe that know what it means; but made uſe of as a more frightful Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, to thoſe poor ſouls, that hardly underſtand what it ſignifies. To ſuch it ſerves onely as a Watch-word to fall on, without examining whether there be any occaſion for it or no; 'tis but dreſſing up a Lamb in a Bears Skin and ſetting on the Maſtiffs; the ignorant Currs will ſoon worry the moſt innocent creature, without diſcovering the Cheat; This terrible word <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> has much the ſame effect with the unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible and fearful dargon of Witches, of Juggling Devils, and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures in the Black-Art; It charms the people into an inconſiderate horror and deteſtation of ſome perſons, they know not why, nor where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; Suſpends all the ſuggeſtions of reaſon and humanity, ſo long as the raging fit of Exorciſm endures; But when a little time has cool'd the poſſeſt Lunaticks into more ſedate reflexion, and common ſenſe; the motives to all this beaſtly rage are found very trifling, or quite falſe, and unaccountable; Thoſe <hi>mercenary Forces</hi> which this
<hi>Aſſociator</hi> talks of, either were thoſe which were raiſed even by the conſent of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which was implyed in their granting a ſupply for their Pay; Or elſe he only means His <hi>Majeſties Guard;</hi> which I agree with him<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97305:10"/>are ſtill kept up, and for very good purpoſe too. If he means the former I am ſo far of his opinion that they were <hi>mercenary Forces;</hi> for they took pay to die as other Souldiers do, ſome of them being Ship't over into <hi>Flanders,</hi> according to the deſign they were raiſed for, and there knock't in the head by the
<hi>French;</hi> But that they were all muſter'd up to cut our Throats, to introduce an <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> with the Sword, and Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre all that oppos'd it, are certainly ſurmiſes as groundleſs as Jealouſies can invent, and like thoſe reports of the <hi>French</hi> landing at
<hi>Purbeck,</hi> and the Battels that were ſeen in the Air, or of the modern Dr. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> that flew from St. <hi>Omers</hi> to <hi>Salamanca;</hi> And if the baſeneſs of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldiers that were liſted, and their Officers affection to Popery ſhall warrant ſuch ſuſpicions; I don't ſee how 'tis poſſible for His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty upon the moſt pleaſing account, to raiſe an Army without ſuch mean beggerly fellows in it, and defend his Officers from being ſuſpected as Papiſts, ſo long as there are onely <hi>poor men</hi> that will take common pay, and <hi>diſaffected perſons</hi> to create ſuch Jealouſies; And what can ſuch ſuſpicions terminate in, but to make the <hi>credulous,</hi> and thoſe that won't believe fairly diſpatch one another, about a quarrel Whether their buſineſs is to be done by a <hi>third?</hi> a pretty way to make an end of the diſpute, and themſelves together: And then by the
<hi>Aſſociator</hi>'s leave, ſuch ſuſpicious thoughts, not only reflect on the integrity of ſo merciful a <hi>Prince,</hi> who is grown almoſt gray under his clemency; and very unlikely to take much comfort in his
<hi>Mercenary Forces;</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary ſway</hi> in his old age; which would but ſerve to diſcompoſe that remnant of Life, we commonly deſire to paſs in the <hi>greateſt</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility: But theſe ſurmiſes detract alſo from the prudence and honeſty of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> that firſt mov'd for their raiſing, and voted a Subſidy for their pay; and ſure he is too tender of the honour of that Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, to fancy they would make their fellow Subjects contribute to their own ruine, and buy their ſlavery at the expence of <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Moneys.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If he means the <hi>Guards,</hi> (which is very probable, becauſe he ſays <hi>ſtill kept up in and about the City of</hi> London) then I deny that they are <hi>to the Terrour and Amazement of all good People,</hi> for none but the <hi>bad</hi> are concerned for it; and 'tis ſtrange that thoſe which are ſo much for the <hi>preſervation</hi> of his Majeſty's Perſon, won't allow of a competent Guard to preſerve him from the Bullet of a <hi>Pickering,</hi> or the Blunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſs of Mr.
<hi>Colledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet theſe Gentlemen that are ſo mightily apprehenſive, of an unaccountable Danger of <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and its being ſet up by the King's Guards, are the very ſame perſons that grin at his Majeſty's thanks for his <hi>Declaration</hi> to govern by Law; blazoning that gracious act to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt party per pale, of weakneſs and impertinencie; and this they do with theſe their two bandied argumentations; Firſt, That ſuch a Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Declaration argues too great condeſcention in a <hi>Monarch,</hi> and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly makes him Appeal to his
<hi>Subjects:</hi> And ſecondly, That the declaring his intention to rule by Law, was as impertinent, as the thanks for it unneceſſary; becauſe that by thoſe Laws, and his Coronation Oath, his Majeſty is obliged to do it: I think I have expreſs'd their meaning in as civil terms as they uſually complement his Majeſty withal: And now they may fairly give me leave to tell my own ſenſe and judgment of theſe their ſentiments, and opinions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97305:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>In my poor Apprehenſion, this gracious Declaration, ſeems <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> all their froward Petitions; And will theſe bawling Bratts not ſo much as be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the very Rattles they cry for? They ſtill bawl'd for frequent Parliaments, and here the King promiſes they ſhall have them.
<hi>Popery</hi> muſt be kept out, and <hi>Property</hi> ſecured; And in this he declares to preſerve the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and protect them in their <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Priviledges;</hi> The dread of <hi>A bitrary Power</hi> was the Burden in all thoſe Papers and Parchments they preſented; And there they are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that he will govern according to
<hi>Laws,</hi> and take them for his ſole Meaſures: And now muſt the ſame factious Scriblers, that writ ſuch <hi>ſmooth Panegyrick</hi> on all their <hi>Petitions,</hi> be hired to make ſuch <hi>Satyrical Animadverſions</hi> on his Majeſties <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring</hi> to gratify them? And ſhall the <hi>King</hi> be urg'd and vex'd into Compliance with all their petulant Requeſts, and then have his good Nature traduc'd for Eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Folly; And ſhall both <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> by turns abuſe the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſecure an Odium upon it, by making <hi>both Extreams</hi> ſerve for the purpoſe? If ſo, for God's ſake let them ſhew me the Poſſibility, of keeping up a Monarchy, amongſt ſuch perverſe and implacable Republicans; and as for the Condeſcention they talk of, his Majeſty is ſomewhat beholden to theſe Gentlemen, for being ſo jealous of his Honour. But I would ask them what other way could be taken to bring his Majeſties Subjects into right underſtanding of his good Inclinations towards them; Theſe Arguers are Conſcious to themſelves, with what black Repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they have blemiſh'd his Government; and to whom ſhall the King appeal for his Juſtification, but to his poor Subjects that are ſcared out of their Loyalty by their falſe, and ſcandalous Suggeſtions? Won't they allow the <hi>King,</hi> what is granted to the moſt profligate <hi>Wretch,</hi> and <hi>Criminal</hi> at a Bar, not ſo much as to make his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; not to have the benefit of every <hi>common Engliſh Man;</hi> And what they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves would expect, if they had their Deſerts, and were arraigned for Treaſon? Sure they ſhow themſelves moſt inveterate Traytors, that after they have repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented their Prince as a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> would put him out of a poſſibility, of ſhewing himſelf <hi>Gracious</hi> and <hi>Merciful;</hi> they know they have a great advantage with the Rabble a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their King upon even Terms; why then muſt he be Libell'd, and not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to venture a Reply? And why ſhall his Majeſty be denied, what their <hi>Hamburg Sheriff</hi> did attempt, to vindicate himſelf in Print? All the Anſwer they can make to it is, That then the People will be brought into their Wits again, and they will loſe the benefit they make of their Diſtraction.</p>
            <p>The other Whirlbat which they flouriſh about mightily, and put into the Hands of every young Combatant, that has a mind to skirmiſh for the Cauſe, is briefly this; That both the King and the Thanks were needleſs, becauſe the King could not do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe by Law, and his Oath<hi>:</hi> But this is like all the reſt of their Arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Government, full of Cavil and Spite.</p>
            <p>We will grant them the <hi>King</hi> can't bring in <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> by Law; but if they tell the <hi>People</hi> that it will be brought in without it, is the King bound by Law to tell them he intends no ſuch thing? Theſe factious Gentlemen are as much bound by the Law, and their Oaths of Allegiance, to live like dutiful Subjects, and to love their Soveraign; and ſhould they declare thus much to their King under their Hands (as they would do, did they really love him,) I fancy they would be very much netled, ſhould not his Majeſty return them ſo much as Thanks for ſuch a Teſtimony, and perhaps grumble too if they were not prefer'd for ſuch a work of Superarro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; Though all this while they are as much obliged by their Oaths to obey, as he is to protect, but yet theſe reciprocal Aſſurances on both ſides may be meerly voluntary. Suppoſe ſome of theſe Arguers met with a ſuſpected Band of licentious Libertines, whom they thought neither the Law of God or Man could deterr from committing any Villany; would not they thank this Banditi for aſſuring them of a ſafe Paſſage, without Plundering or Murder? I appeal to the whole Kingdom whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome of our ſuſpitious Wretches do not daily repreſent the King and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil as dangerous altogether, as any ſuch parcel of Ruſſians, ſuch as would be for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaving the Nation, and cutting of Throats with our <hi>Aſſociators mercenary Forces:</hi> And muſt not the King be permitted to wipe off ſuch black Scandals? expel ſuch Panick Fears, and be thank'd by his Loyal Subjects, for ſuch comfortable Promiſes? In ſhort if they are ſatisfied that the King cannot Rule but by the Law, why do they dread ſo much an
<hi>Arbitrary Power?</hi> If they are afraid he will Rule without it, why won't they <hi>thank</hi> him for his Aſſurance to the contrary? This Digreſſion is ſo fur<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97305:11"/>a pertinent Comment on the laſt Paragraph we handled in the <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> as it clears his Majeſty from deſigning an <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Sway; which the bold
<hi>Aſſociator</hi> would inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate. And now we will proceed to compare the reſt of his <hi>excellent</hi> Stuff.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Aſſociat.</note>
               <hi>Moreover</hi> J. D.
<hi>of</hi> Y. <hi>having publickly own'd the Popiſh Religion,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>I will never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that the ſaid</hi> J. D. <hi>of</hi> Y. <hi>or any other who hath any way adhered to him, and the Papiſts,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>ſhall be admitted to the Succeſſion of the Crown of</hi> England;
<hi>But by all lawful Means, and by force of Arms will oppoſe him, and indeavour to ſubdue and deſtroy him, and all his Adherents, that intend to ſet up his pretended Title.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Holy League <hi>June</hi> 6.</note>
               <hi>That I will according to my Power and Vocation, aſſiſt the Forces raiſed by both Houſes of Parliament, againſt the Forces raiſed by the King without their Conſent.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Solemn Leag. Negat. Oath.</note>I. A. B. <hi>Do ſwear from my Heart, that I will neither directly, nor indirectly adhere unto, or willingly aſſiſt the King in this Cauſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And that my coming and ſubmitting to this Parliament, is without any Deſign whatſoever.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Now I would have any one tell me what will be the difference between aſſiſting the Forces of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> againſt thoſe of the <hi>King;</hi> ſwearing neither directly, or indirectly to adhere to his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> and this Clauſe of <hi>Fighting, Subduing, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling, Deſtroying</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> and all his <hi>Adherents,</hi> when as much a King as ever his father was; which is ſuppoſed and implyed in this Clauſe of the <hi>Aſſociation;</hi> And that all this ſhall be done, when he comes to the Crown, and ſeeks to ſet up his <hi>pretended Title?</hi> But why muſt his Title only be <hi>pretended,</hi> when he will have as much right to wear the Crown, as the Head upon which it is now ſo miraculouſly placed? What can be the reſult of this, but that thoſe men who will think his Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle then but <hi>pretended,</hi> have but little better Opinion of his preſent Majeſtie's? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly upon the ſame Ground that they will not admit him to the Throne, they may pull the preſent King out of it<hi>:</hi> for it is but rejecting the Duke for <hi>giving Life and Birth to the Plot,</hi> and the King for <hi>conniving</hi> at the <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> (that horrid accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation wherewith ſome Traytors have already traduced his Majeſty,) and then fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel Government of old <hi>England;</hi> good Night to the beſt tempered Monarchy in the World.</p>
            <p>But then for the Clauſe of all <hi>Adherents</hi> to be deſtroyed too, 'Tis ſuch an unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted piece of Maſſacre, that for ought I ſee half the Nation muſt be forc'd to ſwim in their own Blood by theſe <hi>tender Lovers</hi> of their Country, and theſe Patriots put in for a more barbarous cutting of Throats than that of the <hi>Danes</hi> in the ſame <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> that of <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> or
<hi>Piedmont</hi> in <hi>Italy:</hi> This word <hi>Adherent</hi> muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the extirpating the <hi>whole Line</hi> of Succeſſion, notwithſtanding it is pretended only in oppoſition to the next
<hi>Heir;</hi> For it does the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> his buſineſs, whom they all acknowledg a Proteſtant Prince, as much as if he were the greateſt Bigot of <hi>Rome;</hi> it is but ſaying he <hi>adheres</hi> to his own Father-in-Law, one from whoſe Blood he muſt derive ſome of his Pretenſions, and then the Proteſtant Prince muſt be deſtroyed too, according to the word of the Aſſociation, <hi>as an Enemy to Laws, Religion, and Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now at laſt comes a Paragraph, not to be parallel'd by the old <hi>Covenants</hi> only becauſe fuller of Treaſon, and Rebellion, The obeying of the Parliament in For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty two, and Forty three without a King, was pretended ſomewhat warrantable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Majeſty had unhappily paſſed an Act for Triennial Parliaments, and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother afterwards for their perpetual ſitting; But this Gentleman without any more Ceremonies, without expecting ſuch an unreaſonable Grant from the King; reſolves that Affairs ſhall be carried on with ſuch a reſolute piece of Treaſon, that none but deſperate Men and mad, ſuch as had bid Defiance to the Laws of God and Man, would ever ingage in; which read <hi>Verbatim,</hi> if it be poſſible for any Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Heart that loves his King and Country, to have ſo much Patience.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Aſſociat.</note>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">And leſt this juſt and pious Work ſhould by any means be obſtructed, or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, for want of Diſcipline and Conduct, or an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> evil minded Perſons under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of raiſing Forces for the ſervice of this Aſſociation, ſhould attempt or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Diſorders, we will follow ſuch Orders as we ſhall from time to time receive from this preſent Parliament, whilſt it ſhall be ſitting; or the major part of the Members of both Houſes ſubſcribing this Aſſociation, when it ſhall be prorogued or diſſolved, and obey ſuch Officers as ſhall by them be ſet over us in the ſeveral Countries, Cities, and Burroughs, until the next meeting of this and another Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; and will then ſhew the ſame Submiſſion and Obedience unto it, and thoſe who ſhall be of it.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:97305:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>I don't doubt but had this
<hi>Aſſociator</hi> been known to both Houſes of Parliament, their profeſſed Loyalty is ſuch, they would have voted his head to be preferred to that honourable place among the Traitors on the Bridge; A juſt requital for paying ſuch a Treaſonable deference to that honourable Aſſembly; and ſo boldly complementing them without their leave into Rebellion; A
<hi>Pious Work</hi> indeed, and ſuch as I don't doubt, without a ſeaſonable repentance and an inſinite Mercy, will damn the Contriver.
<hi>And leſt any evil minded Perſons ſhould commit Diſorders.</hi> A very careful Patriot certainly, one who will not ſuffer ſo much as a little diſorder to be committed; But it would be a little hard for the poor Mouſe that picks a little hole in the Bread to be caught by the neck by the Thief that ſtole the whole Loaf; <hi>Strickt diſcipline</hi> indeed! that makes the leaſt diſorder in raiſing of Forces ſo criminal and obnoxious; and yet the muſtering them up to rebel, a work <hi>Pious</hi> and meritorious. Sure the Contriver of this work is not ſo well acquainted with the Houſe of Commons, and their Priviledges, as he would be thought to be; or elſe is reſolved to act and forge in ſpight of all equity and truth. For none that have ſtretch't the Power of that Aſſembly to its utmoſt extent ever allowed it a right of ſitting like ſo many petty Kings in
<hi>Repreſentative;</hi> To iſſue out Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, raiſe Forces, and command obedience from their fellow Subjects.</p>
            <p>I confeſs we had a Parliament that did all this, raiſed an Army, made their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, fought their King, but ſure this
<hi>Aſſociator</hi> can't be ſuch a Villain to think the late Repreſentatives of the Nation, would all have commenced Traitors; and after a moſt inconſiſtant rate, imitated that Parliament in 41. Which ſome of they themſelves by particular <hi>Act</hi> ſince have declared guilty of Rebellion, nay to outdo and tranſcend them in their Treaſon, to ſit in oppoſition to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Command, whereas thoſe did by his unhappy Permiſſion. But this bold <hi>Aſſociator</hi> can go further yet; reſolves the ſitting Houſe ſhall not only be obeyed as the Supream and Legiſlative power of the Nation, but that the <hi>Major Part</hi> of thoſe
<hi>Members</hi> whom he civilly ſuppoſes ready to ſubſcribe, after
<hi>Prorogation,</hi> after <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> ſhall be ſubmitted to, as inveſted with an higher Supremacy then any would be willing to allow his preſent Majeſty; and that this ſelect Committee in their Reſpective
<hi>Countries, Cities,</hi> and <hi>Burroughs,</hi> like ſo many Stadt-holders in their ſeveral <hi>Provinces,</hi> ſhall create Officers, muſter their Armies, fall a plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering again of Delinquents, and hanging up every <hi>Malignant Dog</hi> that dares but ſhew his teeth or wagg his Tayl; but all this while we muſt not imagine this to be a deſign to ſet up a
<hi>Republick.</hi> The Contriver of all this horrid Treaſon and Rebellion, was only ſome bold impudent Scribler, ſome little factious fellow of a
<hi>Ribband Club.</hi> I wiſh ſuch a Deſign were only in the ſingle heart of ſome poor ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary raſcally Traitor; I fancy then we ſhould quickly have his heart out with his bowels; I fancy the Rogue would hardly lie ſo long <hi>incognitò</hi> or meet with a Stickling
<hi>Ignoramus.</hi> But if ever the Deſign take in the Kingdom, we ſhall ſee ſome of our loſtieſt Cedars will aſpire to the Reputation of having brought it about, and not ſuffer every factious Muſhroom that juſt railed againſt the Government aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the glory of having ſubverted it too; If there be ſuch a brave party ready to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe this excellent deſign (as he ſeems to inſinuate that drew it up,) his Majeſty certainly has more need to double his Guards for his own preſervation, then to diſmiſs them to pleaſe ſuch dangerous <hi>Aſſociators;</hi> and none that have read the common Apologue of the Sheeps being worried by the Wolves aſſoon as perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to diſmiſs their Dogs, but from the Fable can deduce ſo good a Moral as to ſee through the ſhallowneſs of their diſguis'd Intentions, and keep themſelves from being circumvented with ſuch another cheat. I wonder what ſhould make this Politician think ſuch a <hi>Major Part</hi> of <hi>Members</hi> ſo great a <hi>Part</hi> of the Government too as ſingly to require obedience; would it not be as much Treaſon to ſwear fealty to them, as if it were done to perſons that were nothing of that Politick Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? Perhaps with this <hi>Aſſociator</hi> and men of his Principles, the <hi>Swearing only</hi> to obey Members of that honourable Aſſembly much extenuates the guilt of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeying their Prince, but yet he is for ſubmitting to the Orders of thoſe that have no Relation to it, <hi>Diſbanded Members</hi> that have no more ſhare in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment then a petulant Officer in the Company from which he is caſhiered; I know theſe Idolatrous Adorers of their own created Gods, have ſuch ſtrange Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of their deiſied Creatures; that they can't imagine them to be reduced by the breath of a King into their primitive Stations, from which by that very mouth<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97305:12"/>they were called, can't imagine that ſuch a dignified thing, after having once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented the ſenſe of his whole Corporation, to be able to commence again a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Subject, and to have no more underſtanding than his Electors. Be it ſo, ſtill there is no reaſon why this Gentleman muſt be ſuppoſed to retain ſomewhat of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty too, only becauſe it has been, and look'd upon a King; do more than they will allow his Majeſty, carry his Power with him wherever he goes, and in his little <hi>Burrough</hi> make Orders, and Laws, only becauſe he hath voted in the place where they are legally made. Theſe are ſuch Extravagancies in Opinion, that not a diſcreet Perſon that ever ſerved his Country in that Capacity, but will deteſt to be thought guilty of, nothing but the wild Conceits of ſome City Mechanicks, or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Clodpates that ſend them thither, or the treaſonable Inſinuations of ſuch an <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociator</hi> to ſubvert the Government.</p>
            <p>The cloſe of all theſe <hi>Solemn Leagues</hi> are ſtill the ſame, very <hi>pious</hi> indeed and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Aſſociation.</note>
               <hi>Neither will we for any reſpect of Perſons, or Cauſes, or for fear of Reward ſeparate our ſelves from this Aſſociation, or fail in proſecution thereof during our Lives, upon Pain of being by the reſt of us proſecuted as perjured Perſons, and publick Enemies to God, the King, and our Native Country, to which Pains and Puniſhment we do voluntarily ſubmit our ſelves,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Scotch ſolemn League.</note>
               <hi>That we ſhall aſſiſt and defend all that enter into this League and Covenant: Nor ſuffer our ſelves Directly, nor indirectly, by whatſoever Combination, Perſwaſion, or Terror, to be divided, or withdrawn from this bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, and Conjunction; all which we ſhall do as in the ſight of God, in the preſence of the Almighty, the ſearcher of all Hearts, as I ſhall anſwer it at the great Day, when the Secrets of all Hearts ſhall be diſcloſed.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Holy League 6. of <hi>June.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>I will likewiſe aſſiſt all other Perſons that ſhall take this Oath, in what they ſhall do in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance hereof; and this Vow and Covenant I make in the preſence of Almighty God, the ſearcher of all Hearts, with a true Intention to perform the ſame, as I ſhall anſwer it at the great Day, when the ſecrets of all Hearts ſhall be diſcloſed.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>If theſe Inſtruments of Hell were to be compared with any thing beſides them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, I ſhould aſſimulate them to the Serpent I have read of in <hi>Pliny</hi>'s natural Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which he calls
<hi>Amphisbaena;</hi> deſcribing it with a ſmooth, delicate Head at both ends; and in thoſe two fine Extremities all the Cunning of the crafty ſubtil Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal ſeems to be lodged, while all the other parts beſides are nothing but Venom, and Viper; All theſe ſubtile Engines you may obſerve to begin with abundance of cunning Inſinuations, as if all were done for the real Advance of Religion and Piety, with a <hi>having before our Eyes the Glory of God, &amp;c.</hi> See Scotch Coven. With a <hi>finding to the Grief of our Hearts, that the Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuits,</hi> vid. Pref. to the Aſſoc. And then all conclude, in calling it a <hi>bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion for the Glory of God;</hi> vid. Solem. Leag. <hi>A righteous End, and pious Work:</hi> See Aſſoc. All with the Name of <hi>God</hi> at both Ends; whil'ſt all the Bowels and Entrails of theſe Monſters, are full of the
<hi>Devil;</hi> full of Venom againſt the <hi>Government;</hi> Treaſon againſt the <hi>King;</hi> And Lies to the very Face of that <hi>God</hi> they ſo ſolemnly Invoke. Well, then it ſeems by the reſolute Cloſe of this <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> that <hi>no reſpect of Perſons or Cauſes, Fear, or Reward,</hi> ſhall make them deſert their Fellows and Aſſociates; Stout Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions indeed! and ſo true to the Cauſe, as to make it a ſort of Treaſon to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire the giving it up: With a kind of Martial Law to puniſh the Delinquents, as a Council of War does thoſe that fly from their Colours, or yield up a Garriſon; And yet all this while think it not ſo much as a <hi>Peccadillo,</hi> to Plot againſt the State, and Rebel againſt their Soveraign. For certainly if no <hi>Perſons</hi> or
<hi>Cauſes,</hi> muſt make them deſert ſo wicked a Conſpiracy, or permit any ſingle Conſpirator to turn an honeſt Renegado; Then all his Majeſties Proclamations like thoſe of his Father's, for laying down their Arms, muſt be anſwered with a <hi>Remonſtrance;</hi> They may get ſome young Spawn of <hi>old Oliver</hi> for their General; and in ſpight of King and Laws, march with their Colours flying, and Drums beating, throughout all the Kingdom from <hi>Barwick</hi> to the <hi>Mount;</hi> and all this muſt be done if enjoyned by the <hi>Major Party</hi> of <hi>Members.</hi> Not only upon thoſe common Obligations, moſt Laws bind Vaſſals to Obedience,
<hi>viz.</hi> by being <hi>Penal</hi> or <hi>Capital;</hi> not only ſuch light Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Vengeance muſt follow the violating the Contract, but Damnation too, and every daſtard Delinquent, that hath not an Heart, like one of <hi>Matchiavil</hi>'s compleat Rogues, ſtout enough to go through all this Villany; muſt be <hi>proſecuted</hi> with a Pillory here, and
<hi>Damn'd</hi> as a perjured Perſon hereafter.</p>
            <p>I know the Italian Bandities, and our Engliſh Highway-Man, though but<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97305:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>common Out-laws on the ſame terms the Subſcribers of this <hi>Aſſociation</hi> would be, puniſh one another many times by mutual agreement, and that according to the Penalties of thoſe very Laws of the Kingdom they daily violate. But however though ſuch exact Juſtice be obſerved amongſt Thieves and Robbers it cannot extenuate the guilt of thoſe Murders and Villanies they commit. And why all the Blood that is ſhed, all the Plunder that is committed by ſuch a ſelect Band of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanteers is not as much a Violation of the Laws, as Murder and Robery, I cannot underſtand; then it ſeems alſo no <hi>Hope of Fear or Reward</hi> muſt ſeparate theſe reſolute Fellows; If ſo, I would ask theſe Gentlemen, whether the <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> the Hopes of Heaven, and Happineſs may not alſo be excluded by ſo univerſal a Negative? If they ſay they only mean by it the allurements of Men, or Terrours of ſome earthly Powers; Then it had been but prudently done to have mollified it with ſome ſuch Limitation. If they make no ſuch excuſe for it, then I think it ſtands ſtill a daring piece of Atheiſm, and reſolute profaneneſs; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were they to <hi>ſeparate themſelves during Lives,</hi> ſo this is a moſt excellent and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous proſecution indeed, they are not ſo much as to think themſelves abſolved from this Oath, though the reaſons and occaſions for taking it were quite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved and obviated, for 'tis ſuch an indiſpenſable Obligation as muſt not ceaſe but with their breath; and they ſwear to hold their Combination by the ſame Tenure ſome do their places with a <hi>Durante Vita,</hi> ſo that ſuppoſe by an untimely death, or a natural one, the <hi>Duke,</hi> that unhappy Burden of this lamentable Song, were removed; they ſtill oblige themſelves to obey what Orders they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from thoſe
<hi>Perpetual Dictators,</hi> ſo long as they enjoy Breath and Life to put them in Execution. And all this notwithſtanding a ſurviving King or Proteſtant Succeſſor, how near this would have come to the nature of a Common-wealth, I ſubmit to the determination even of thoſe men that think all Republican Deſigns at this time ſo ridiculous and impoſſible.</p>
            <p>Thus having with as much patience and moderation, as ſuch a provoking Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject would permit; paralell'd, examined, the nature, tendency of this ſpecious <hi>Aſſociation</hi> it ſelf by comparing each particular Paragraph, we will now make ſome obſervations on the whole complicated Piece of <hi>Digeſted Treaſon:</hi> And then expoſe thoſe little Subterfuges, that Varniſh of reaſon and argumentation they are forced to fly to, that defend it like ſinking Mariners, catching at every little Board and Plank, to buoy up the head of ſo deſperate a Cauſe.</p>
            <p>This whole Scheam of Rebellion will upon a careful peruſal be found, in ſome places of ſuch an unlimited extent; in others full of mental reſervation; ſometimes you meet with a deep Equivocation; then with a plain Lie<hi>:</hi> here ſome factious inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and at laſt perfect treaſonable Poſitions, that one would ſwear the Council of a
<hi>Conclave, Hell,</hi> and a <hi>Republick,</hi> had all conſulted the form and manner of the drawing it up. And each inſerted its Paragraph, according to their ſeveral abilities, of <hi>Equivocating, Lying,</hi> and <hi>Speaking Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt none are <hi>Excluded</hi> that will but come in and take this Oath; For they ſwear to protect all ſuch as ſhall enter into it
<hi>in juſt performance of the true Intent and meaning of it;</hi> ſo that if Turk, Jew, Infidel, or any Heretick in the World that is no profeſs'd Papiſt, come and ſubſcribe, he is preſently to be protected and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended: I know that in the Preface to this <hi>Pious Work,</hi> 'tis only extended to all <hi>True Proteſtants;</hi> but that general appellation is ſo indefinite, that I do not ſee why it may not comprehend an Army of
<hi>Tartars,</hi> if they will but land here and proteſt againſt the King and Government; then it is ſo <hi>Extenſive</hi> that all
<hi>Adherents</hi> muſt be <hi>deſtroyed;</hi> ſo that the <hi>King</hi> by denying his Royal Aſſent to diſpoſſeſs his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his unqueſtionable Right, and the <hi>Lords</hi> the paſſing the Bill in the Higher Houſe, being in all reaſon to be judged <hi>Adherents</hi> to the
<hi>Duke;</hi> muſt be cut off e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mothers Son, which certainly would be a worſe piece of buſineſs for the <hi>Peers,</hi> then heretofore their being Voted <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeleſs; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeleſs Trunks</hi> they would make them indeed now, when by ſuch an <hi>Aſſociation</hi> they would go near to loſe their heads.</p>
            <p>Secondly, all this old Chiming and Ding Dong about
<hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> that muſt ring through the Country on the communicating this new <hi>Covenant,</hi> and charm the liſtning Clod-pate like a merry Peal of Bells on a Holyday, is nothing elſe but
<hi>Mental Reſerve</hi> and meer <hi>Equivocation;</hi> For firſt by the name of <hi>Liberty</hi> cannot be meant that of enjoying the Freedom of their perſons from confinement;<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97305:13"/>as every good Subject may well expect, ſo long as he lives in Conformity to the Laws, that would juſtly confine, and puniſh him if he did not; for
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen it would have been but a piece of impertinency to have inſerted it; for the whole Nation at preſent enjoys all this; therefore it muſt neceſſarily follow that all that can be employed in this Ambiguous Phraſe <hi>Liberty,</hi> by ſuch
<hi>Aſſociators,</hi> is a <hi>Liberty</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling with impunity, a
<hi>Licenſe</hi> to perpetrate all thoſe villaines, for the obtaining of which the ſpecious Pretence of <hi>Liberty</hi> can but poſſibly be ſuggeſted; and which indeed is now adays upon all occaſions ſo cunningly pretended that I don't ſee but in a ſhort time the whole Kingdom may ſet up for <hi>Levellers</hi> and <hi>Libertines;</hi> every poor beggarly Raſcal plunder his wealthy Neighbour till he make the ſquares e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,—every bloudy Villain ſtab, ſhoot, and murder all that oppoſe his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, whilſt the ſuppreſſing this Barbariſm ſhall be thought an infringing of <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> Forbidding the <hi>Iſraelites to ſpoil the Aegyptians,</hi> and then no wonder if they <hi>murmur againſt Moſes and Aaron in their Tents:</hi> And then by <hi>Property</hi> can never be meant the keeping of their Poſſeſſions in quiet: ſo long as there is no one that diſturbs them in it: But if they are reſolved to be their own Tormentors out them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from their Tenements, by voluntary ſlight, run away as if they would leave themſelves behind: haunted by their own Shadows: fancy <hi>French</hi> Armies at <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck,</hi> Navies at
<hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and then depopulate their Habitations of their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: Certainly this can't be charged as a Severity on the Government, as ſeizing their Properties, or elſe Careleſſneſs in the Magiſtrate in not defending them; If the <hi>Rabble</hi> will like a Flock of <hi>Crows,</hi> or <hi>Wild-Geeſe,</hi> at the Garring or Cackling of one of their
<hi>Centinels,</hi> preſently take the Alarm, and with a terrible Cry be ſtreight on the Wing, although there be no Guns in the Field, or Nots in the way; Sure they may thank themſelves too for their own Diſturbance. And 'tis evident to the moſt diſcontented Wretch, though his froward Soul force him to lye even in deſpight of <hi>Grace,</hi> and the Suggeſtions of
<hi>Conſcience</hi> to the contrary<hi>:</hi> That ſince the
<hi>King's</hi> Reſtoration, the <hi>Libertie,</hi> not ſo much, as of the meaneſt Subject, has ever been Infringed, or Violated, unleſs merited by his <hi>own Guilt,</hi> and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by the <hi>Law;</hi> nor ſo much as one Tittle of <hi>Property</hi> denyed to the Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, beſides what hath been forfeited by Rebelling againſt his Majeſty, or the Laws of the Kingdom; What there was before, thoſe beſt know that ſuffered by the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of that Uſurpation; So that all that can be meant by theſe
<hi>Aſſociators,</hi> when they cry out <hi>Propertie,</hi> is but ſuppoſing themſelves to have a Right, where they have none at all, and then cry out they are denyed their Share in this and that, when all the while they have no right to the <hi>Dividend;</hi> So that I think the reſerv'd Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman that drew it up, might have been more free and open; and in plain terms be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoke the People, as a certain <hi>Ignoramus Criminal</hi> is ſaid to have done; Look you my Friends, there is a black Man at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> keeps a great deal of Room and Land, of which we were once in quiet Poſſeſſion. And I don't ſee why we ſhould for go thoſe
<hi>Properties</hi> that were held <hi>(vi &amp; armis,)</hi> by our Grandfathers, 'tis but knocking the <hi>Guards</hi> on the Head, and in with our Blunderbuſſes, make thoſe Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coated Lobſters ſwim a little in their own Blood; <hi>Seize</hi> the <hi>Heir,</hi> and the <hi>Inheritance</hi> is our own again.</p>
            <p>Then for its black <hi>Lyes,</hi> and <hi>Contradictions;</hi> They are like the Darkneſs of Hell it ſelf, ſo groſs that they may be felt; what an impudent piece of Falſhood is it to perſwade a Nation, that it is guilty of a thing, of which to its very ſelf it is no way Conſcious; and make it ſwear that the <hi>Guards</hi> are kept up to the <hi>Terror, and Amazement of all good People,</hi> when all the while they believe no ſuch thing; Strange that this <hi>Amazing</hi> ſit ſhould on the ſudden ſurpriſe us, of which we have had not ſo much as a Symptom this twenty Years. I ſuppoſe it would puzzle this <hi>quacking Stateſman</hi> to give the true cauſe of this ſudden <hi>ſhivering</hi> Diſtemper in the Body
<hi>Politick,</hi> as much as it doth moſt <hi>Phyſicians</hi> truly to define the matter of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues</hi> in the <hi>Natural;</hi> But the
<hi>Aſſociator</hi> preſumes much upon the Ignorance of the People, or his own Wit and Parts; And that <hi>they</hi> are as ready to ſwallow a groſs <hi>Lye,</hi> as <hi>he</hi> is to ram it down with an <hi>Oath;</hi> Or elſe ſure he would not be ſo bold as to perſwade them that one or two thouſand Men in Arms, would cut the Throats of ſo many Millions; this is eſtabliſhing Paradoxes on the Credulity of Fools and Idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots; 'Tis the Happineſs theſe man have to make the wildeſt Extreams ſubſervient to their Cauſe; The <hi>Infidelity</hi> of a prejudiced <hi>Ignoramus</hi> keeps it up on the one ſide, and the <hi>Credulouſneſs</hi> of thoſe that are truly <hi>Ignorant,</hi> muſt be the Buttereſs on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97305:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>I have heard of a Fellow that was often drunk and Lunatick, and in either of thoſe ſits had ſuch dreadfull Appearances of Fiery Dragons, and ſtrange Viſions, and the Deluſion of his fancy ſo violent, that he could never be ſatisfied till he had impoſed the ſame belief on all thoſe that were about him, who to avoid the troubleſomeneſs of the Impoſtor were forced to ſeign themſelves Spectators too. I think this will be all the <hi>Terror,</hi> and <hi>Amazement</hi> the
<hi>Wiſe</hi> People and the <hi>Good</hi> will lie under, and as for the
<hi>Fools,</hi> and <hi>Knaves,</hi> we care not how much they are frightned by ſuch Sir <hi>Eglamores,</hi> the Champions of the State and their <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agons;</hi> and then what a pretty piece of <hi>Contradiction</hi> is it, for them to ſwear to defend his <hi>Royal Majeſties Perſon,</hi> and <hi>Eſtate;</hi> and then in the next line to talk of oppoſing <hi>Arbitrary Power?</hi> which ſeems to me ſomewhat like the proceedings of that Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Judas;</hi> come on with a <hi>Hail Maſter,</hi> and then delivering him to be crucified. Declaring both offenſive, and defenſive War at the ſame time, and againſt the ſame Perſon. For who can be thought to ſet up <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and who can be meant in that expreſſion, but his <hi>Majeſty?</hi> a Prince that has ruled them this twenty years, with a Clemency almoſt to a Crime, and made himſelf the Object of their diſcontent, only by his Gracious Indulgence<hi>:</hi> Laſtly that there are <hi>Treaſonable Poſitions</hi> in it is pretty plain from the laſt Clauſe of obeying their fellow Subjects, ſome little Regiment of a disbanded Committee; when there is an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that makes it high Treaſon, on any Pretence whatſoever to enter into Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination or take up Arms againſt the King; 'tis true this Monſter of a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> ſeems with it's <hi>Head</hi> to defend the Crown and Scepter, but with it's <hi>Tail</hi> laſhes the one from his Majeſties <hi>Head,</hi> and the other out of his <hi>Hand;</hi> deſtroys the Monarchy, erects a Common-wealth, enſlaves the People with the Bait of Freedom, and to ſave the ſilly wretches from <hi>Popery,</hi> damns them to the puniſhment of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and the torments of <hi>Hell:</hi> And now I hope the charge I laid down above is proved in its ſeveral particulars, and from the agreeableneſs of it to ſuch Projectors, from its
<hi>Treaſon</hi> will be thought the contrivance of a <hi>Republican,</hi> from its <hi>Aequivocation</hi> of a <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> from its <hi>Lying</hi> of the <hi>Devil.</hi> And now we ſhall conſider the poor Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments that are uſed by the party to defend it; and the firſt Champion that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the Liſt ſeems armed with all the authority the Supream power of the Nation can inveſt it withall, &amp; ſaid by the Factions Abettors of it to have been the diſcourſe, and Deſign of the <hi>Parliament;</hi> which is the plain inſinuation of the Fore-man, when my Lord <hi>S.</hi> was to be put on his Triall, <hi>vid.</hi> Proceedings at the <hi>Old Baily;</hi> where theſe glancing Interrogatories are ſtill put to Mr. Secretary<hi>:</hi> Don't you know there was a diſcourſe in <hi>Parliament?</hi> Did not you know of ſuch a debate in <hi>Parliament?</hi> Han't you heard there was a talk of
<hi>Aſſociation</hi> in <hi>Parliament?</hi> Prety Queſtions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and is this one of them they took ſo much time for, this all the egg that is laid after ſo much cackling and laying their heads together? I thought a Grand Jury ſuch <hi>Good men</hi> and <hi>true,</hi> were ſworn to fift things impartially, without being Counſel for the Priſoner, in oppoſition to the King<hi>:</hi> If ſo let any man judge how pertinent this Queſtion was to the detecting the truth, and ſince they are ſo tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Interogatories; Quaere whether theſe two or three Quaeries may not as well be put?</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Whether if all the Council aſſigned to</hi> Fitz Harris, <hi>could have pleaded more for his Lordſhip, than theſe Gentlemen of the Grand Inqueſt?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Whether Ignoramus Juries ought not to be conſidered from the Proteſtant Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer; which like their</hi> Thames <hi>is at full Tide in the City, when 'tis Low Water at</hi> White-Hall?</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Whether the Council of the one, or the Jurors of the other were the beter paid, And what is the difference between taking up a Prejudice againſt the Kings Cauſe, and a fee for the Priſoners?</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe Quaeries being civilly propoſed, we'll now make ſome reply to their puzzling Interrogatories, about a <hi>Parliament;</hi> which I look upon as a ſort of rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling <hi>Sphinx,</hi> and like that Monſter, with many forms, and faces, which if not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riddled, they'll be ſure to make it murder the credit of the Kings Evidence. But then if it chance to meet with its <hi>Oedipus,</hi> and be well expounded; why ſhould not theſe Gentlemen and their Cauſe, (to carry on the fable,) break their necks too? we know as well as any of theſe <hi>Good, Honeſt</hi> men, that there was a Bill propoſed in the Houſe of Commons, and that about <hi>Aſſociation</hi> too, they having owned it, and publiſhed it in their Printed Votes, and ſo not only the cloſe, fly inſinuations<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97305:14"/>of their ſubtil Interrogatories. But what then? does it follow this diſcovered pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per was read there too, and every Paragraph of it, amongſt which one is plain Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? ſure that honourable Houſe is but little beholden to thoſe Gentlemen for ſuch ſquinting reflections. But it ſeems ſuch men may make bolder with their Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives, and take as much liberty with their
<hi>Petty Gods,</hi> as a canting Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt does with his <hi>God Almighty.</hi> Then ſecondly were it read there <hi>verbatim</hi> as theſe bold Inſinuators would have the World believe, ſure the bare debating or reading it could not paſs it into an Act too, and make it as ſtatutable, as if the King's <hi>Le Roy vult</hi> had paſſed it into <hi>Law;</hi> if ſo, it had then been pertinently urged as an Argument for the Priſoner, when all the <hi>Old Acts</hi> that make it Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to raiſe Forces without the King, would have been abrogated by this <hi>New one</hi> for tolerating Inſurrection. In the mean time give me leave to think that this Suggeſtion excuſed them no more from bringing the Priſoner to his
<hi>Trial,</hi> then a Vote of the Houſe could have warranted them to pull him out of the <hi>Tower.</hi> And by their leave how do all theſe inſinuations prove the Parliament concerned in it? the moſt that can be gathered from the Circumſtances of Affairs, is, that it muſt be only underſtood of the Houſe of Commons, and now all is out, and what none of them will own when pinch't with it, blabs forth unawares in Confeſſion. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Tongues, thus to betray their Maſters.</p>
            <p>So now we know what they mean by a <hi>Parliament,</hi> it ſeems the Houſe of Commons is the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and they will have this
<hi>Parliament</hi> to exclude the <hi>Duke</hi> by themſelves; their Votes to be Law, and they ſit again as long as they pleaſe, and whether the King will or no; 'tis they muſt go down into their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Burroughs; and according to this <hi>Aſſociation</hi> raiſe the Militia, and make the people ſwear to obey them: If this be the right conſtitution of a
<hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Lord have mercy upon us,</hi> and <hi>God ſave the King,</hi> and no wonder then if the Houſe of Lords were in the late Rebellion Voted uſeleſs, and now declared <hi>Obſtructors of Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Violators of the conſtitution of Parliaments;</hi> and no need will there be for <hi>Repealing an Act of Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> if they can be ſo much traduced, made ſo ſcandalous without it. And give me leave to tell theſe Gentlemen too, that make the name of
<hi>Parliament,</hi> a Juſtification for all their own
<hi>Factiouſneſs,</hi> and a Terrour to all other peoples <hi>Loyalty:</hi> that this complementing that honourable Aſſembly as their <hi>Patrons,</hi> and but other mens <hi>Bugbears</hi> is no ſuch great piece of civility. If you now adays reprimand a fellow for talking irreverently of the King or Council, you are gagg'd preſently with the ſenſe of <hi>Parliament;</hi> tell them the <hi>Duke</hi>'s ſtill the next Succeſſor, you are muzzl'd with the <hi>Bill of Excluſion;</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear veiling your Bonnet to Dr.
<hi>Oats</hi>'s <hi>Gippo,</hi> and he flaps you in the teeth with a
<hi>Parliament;</hi> condemn the Treaſon of this <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> and you are ſtunn'd with ſuch an Interrogatory. Now 'tis certain that none of theſe things ever were the Judgment of <hi>Parliament:</hi> Becauſe neither the <hi>King</hi> nor the Houſe of <hi>Lords</hi> are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver like to be of theſe Opinions; and as for this Scheam of <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the Commons themſelves, never thought on ſuch ſtrange Reſolutions, as are there intended. For as 'tis acknowledged by all that the murder of Juſtice <hi>Godfrey</hi> (which was as imprudent, as barbarous) made the fam'd ſubtilty of the Jeſuit much ſuſpected; and with a prepoſterous piece of Policy helped the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther detection of that Plot, they thought to ſmother in the ſtream of his Blood; ſo 'tis as bad Politicks in our Commonwealths-men to make the <hi>Parliament</hi> Abettors of their proceedings, whilſt it gratifies the <hi>Papiſt</hi> and their Cauſe much more, than that cruel and inconſiderate murder, helps to put off the thorow Examination of that <hi>Helliſh Conſpiracy;</hi> which they themſelves think will never be ſufficiently ſiſted; ſo that 'tis no ſuch Paradox to ſay the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> had an hand in this <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> as well as the <hi>Republicans,</hi> and that both cabal in their <hi>Clubs</hi> for the ſubverting the <hi>State</hi> as well as in their
<hi>Aſſemblies</hi> for the ruining of the <hi>Church;</hi> the Conſults for the one, being carried on at their <hi>Coffee-Houſes;</hi> and for the other, at their <hi>Conventicles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the boldneſs and preſumption that the factious party take, of making their houſe of Commons eſpouſe, and warrant all their Licentiouſneſs, is not only an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe put upon the whole Gentry of the Nation, but directly deſtructive of thoſe fooliſh Deſigns they think to promote by it. I know that which makes them ſo Impudent to ſlur this
<hi>Aſſociation</hi> on that honourable Aſſembly are thoſe Votes that were paſſed the 15<hi>th</hi> and 16<hi>th</hi> and 21<hi>th</hi> of
<hi>Dec.</hi> 1680. The 15<hi>th. Ordered that a Bill be</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97305:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>brought in for an Aſſociation of all his Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects.</hi> The 16. <hi>A Bill for uniting his Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects to the Church of</hi> England, <hi>was read a firſt time;</hi> and on the 21, they addreſs, That his Majeſty would graciouſly be pleaſed to aſſent to an Act for enabling his Proteſtant Subjects, to aſſociate themſelves for the defence of his Perſon. Now
'tis evident by theſe <hi>Bills,</hi> that their intent was to make his Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects unite themſelves to the Church of
<hi>England;</hi> and in order to that, to aſſociate themſelves for the Preſervation of the Defender of their Faith; how far theſe Purpoſes agree with the Subverting the State, and ruining the Church, (the clear intent of this diſcovered <hi>Aſſociation</hi>) I ſubmit to the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of this <hi>grand Inqueſt,</hi> who perhaps may be able to reconcile the Contradiction.</p>
            <p>Then ſuch an <hi>Aſſociation</hi> as this would not only be derogatory from the <hi>Honour</hi> of that Aſſembly, but from the profeſt <hi>Loyalty</hi> of it too: And in God's Name what would they prove by ſuch Arguments, and Suggeſtions; would they make <hi>Treaſon</hi> brood within thoſe <hi>Walls,</hi> as well as within thoſe of their
<hi>City?</hi> Do they deſign that their <hi>Rowſes, Wilmores, Whitakers, Harveys,</hi> ſhall be all their Members in the next <hi>Parliament?</hi> Then perhaps I may not doubt of ſuch an <hi>Aſſociation</hi> to be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But that it was the deſign of the <hi>Parliament</hi> that ſate laſt at <hi>London,</hi> I muſt beg their Pardon if I ſuſpend my Judgment from concurring with theirs. The Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Acquaintance only my poor ſelf had in it, might have made a larger Body of <hi>Proteſting Commons</hi> than there were of <hi>Lords</hi> at <hi>Oxford;</hi> ſuch as would have been very much concern'd, and trembled to have ſeen, the Foundations of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that of their own Walls, ſhaking together. And laſtly ſuch an Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only contradicts it ſelf, and is quite impoſſible; for the very Act of drawing up ſuch an
<hi>Aſſociation</hi> as this, would have made them <hi>de facto,</hi> forfeit their Allegiance to their <hi>Prince;</hi> And then in a moral Sence diſcharge them from being their <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries Repreſentatives;</hi> and they ſhall aſſoon perſwade me that the ſame Perſons that were then in the <hi>Houſe,</hi> were at the ſame time in the <hi>Cellars</hi> to blow it up.</p>
            <p>When they are driven from this hold of a <hi>Parliament;</hi> the next ſeeming place of Strength they fly to is that of an
<hi>Aſſociation</hi> in the 27 of <hi>Queen Elizabeth.</hi> And indeed 'tis ſuch a Refuge, as none but ſuch as are put to flight out of their wits, and all in confuſion would ſeek to ſhelter themſelves in; for 'tis but looking on the Combination that was drawn up for the <hi>Queen</hi>'s defence, and you will quickly ſee how weak an one it is for our
<hi>Adverſaries;</hi> and all the late Rebels might as well have made it their Pretence, for the drawing up their <hi>Covenants;</hi> The whole Drift of that aims at the protecting her Majeſty, againſt all that ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to her Crown; and all along the Form, and Words of it ſeem to denote as if it were the Queens Motion, that had firſt given occaſion for it, rather then that of her Commons. And 'tis obvious that it was done to ſecure her Title againſt the pretenſions of the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Scots,</hi> who lay then in the Tower, and within two years after, in the 29 of her Reign was beheaded. How much the Kings Preſervation was intended in the late
<hi>Aſſociation,</hi> I leave his <hi>Guards</hi> to determine, who had never more need of being doubled; And how much his Majeſty was pleaſed and acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it, the Loyal Nobility and honeſt Hearts that are about him beſt know, and whoſe Number I wiſh may be daily augmented.
<note place="margin">Aſſociation, 27. in Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> time, and <hi>Charles</hi> 2<hi>d.</hi> compared.</note> In the firſt Lines of the <hi>Queens Aſſociation,</hi> they ſtrongly promiſe to defend her
<hi>Soveraignty</hi> and <hi>Supremacy;</hi> and in this they won't allow ſo much as <hi>Guards</hi> for the Defence of the <hi>King's Perſon.</hi> They with <hi>joyful Hearts</hi> acknowledg her a gracious Lady, and that the Queen Reigned to their great Felicity and Comfort, and that they have received the Benefit of <hi>Peace, Wealth,</hi> and Godly Government under her Majeſty, plentifully under her Reign, more then the Nation did under any King before.</p>
            <p>This Aſſoc. with <hi>heavy Hearts conſiders</hi> the King as ſetting up <hi>Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as Popiſhly affected, as
<hi>Waſting, Conſuming</hi> the <hi>Reputation,</hi> the <hi>Strength, Treaſure</hi> of the Nation, and does not ſo much as allow his
<hi>Reign</hi> to have been more <hi>Merciful</hi> than that of the late
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi> ſays that with our whole Power, Bodies, Lives, and Goods, with our Children, and Servants, we will faithfully Serve, and humbly Obey, our ſaid Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lady, againſt all States, Powers, and Dignities,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> ſays that with our joynt and particular Forces, we will Oppoſe and Purſue unto Deſtruction; all that ſhall oppoſe the Juſt and Righteous Ends of this <hi>Aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation;</hi> The Ends I think follow: <hi>to raiſe Forces, to Obey only the ſitting Parliament, or elſe the disbanded Members of a diſſolved one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97305:15"/>In ſhort, all <hi>that</hi> was carried on with the <hi>Queens Advice, Conſent,</hi> and <hi>Privity;</hi> The laſt Clauſes of <hi>this</hi> ſufficiently evidence his Majeſties
<hi>Conſent</hi> never to be expected. That endeavoured to <hi>ſupport</hi> the Crown and Dignity, This to lay both in the Duſt; That <hi>faſtned</hi> the Scepter in the <hi>Queens</hi> Hand, and This <hi>plucks</hi> it out of the
<hi>Kings:</hi> That help't to <hi>ſettle</hi> the Foundations of the
<hi>Government;</hi> This endeavors to <hi>undermine</hi> a ſetled one: That an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of <hi>Loyal Hearts,</hi> and would have <hi>repell'd</hi> the ſtrongeſt Invader; This an <hi>Aſſociation</hi> of
<hi>diſcontented ones,</hi> and will <hi>invite</hi> an Enemy<hi>:</hi> That was a <hi>Legal Combination</hi> of <hi>dutiful</hi> Subjects; <hi>This</hi> can never be ſubſcribed but by <hi>[the Rebellions.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Courſe they take to palliate the Deſign, is by ſaying none of all this was intended to be put in Execution, in the
<hi>King's time;</hi> But only upon his Death, to keep out the <hi>Duke</hi> of
<hi>York.</hi> A very good Defence indeed: and won't that <hi>D.</hi> of
<hi>Y.</hi> be as much a King then as his Royal Brother was before him? Muſt his Highneſs wait their Leaſure to be plac'd in the Throne? and ſhall he paſs for the <hi>Peoples</hi> Heir inſtead of that of the <hi>Crown?</hi> Is there ſuch a diverſity in Rebellion that 'tis lawful againſt
<hi>one</hi> Prince, though not againſt <hi>another?</hi> Or are theſe new Diſtinctions only the Metaphyſicks of Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> and the politick
<hi>Aphoriſms</hi> of his <hi>Commonwealth?</hi> But that this Suggeſtion is improbable and notoriouſly Falſe, appears from this
<hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument</hi> it ſelf; For in it the <hi>preſent King</hi> is accuſed of <hi>Arbitrary Power;</hi> his <hi>preſent Guards</hi> now kept up, to be removed; and the <hi>Sitting, Prorogu'd,</hi> and <hi>Diſſolved Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> are to be obeyed; and alſo ſuch as ſhall be again
<hi>call'd</hi> after ſuch <hi>Prorogation,</hi> and <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſolution.—</hi>When they are reaſon'd out of all their Holds, then at laſt they very fairly
<hi>denie,</hi> the matter of Fact; and disbelieve any ſuch
<hi>Inſtrument</hi> found up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any of their Party by the King's Witneſſes, making it all a <hi>Sham,</hi> and the two <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Perſons that found the Paper, a couple of <hi>perjured</hi> Villains; But I hope they will give the World leave to believe their Teſtimony upon their <hi>Oaths:</hi> before ſuch
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>everations upon nothing but
<hi>Prejudice:</hi> And this ſo ſlatly deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Fact, is like a baffled young Sophiſters anſwering his Opponents Syllogiſms with <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> inſtead of a <hi>non ſequitur:</hi> Now whether the worthy Patriot was
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in whoſe Cuſtody 'twas found; is only between <hi>God</hi> and himſelf, and all <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> is but his <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> only becauſe not <hi>Omniſcient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[And Now] by this time I hope they are ſatisfied how mightily their <hi>new</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of <hi>Aſſociation</hi> agrees with the <hi>old Leagues</hi> and <hi>Covenants;</hi> and how exactly their <hi>late</hi> Tranſactions imitate <hi>thoſe</hi> of the <hi>true Proteſtants</hi> in
<hi>forty one;</hi> The recollection of which they are as much troubled at, as ſick men to ſee themſelves in a Glaſs. But ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re theſe ſort of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> may be more ſurpriſed to find themſelves reſembling <hi>Papiſts</hi> too. And inſtead of having drawn their late <hi>Covenant</hi> from the Records of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> times, to find it but a clear extract of the
<hi>League</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> I am ſure that <hi>Aſſociation</hi> of thoſe <hi>rebellious Papiſts,</hi> thoſe <hi>Catholique Fanaticks</hi> ſuits, better to their Purpoſe, than this they pretend to write by, which only contradicts them; And now we are in the Vein and Humor of drawing
<hi>Parallels</hi> between <hi>Covenants,</hi> I ſhall give them a taſt too, of that in <hi>France</hi> againſt the poor <hi>Hugonots,</hi> who were ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be favoured by the Government, juſt as the
<hi>Catholiques</hi> are ſtill here; and let theſe deluded Zealots ſee, that they tread not only in the footſteps of the <hi>true Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> but alſo of the
<hi>rank Papiſts</hi> of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> in
<hi>France,</hi> and then I hope it will make the moſt impudent of them bluſh, to find themſelves tranſported into ſuch Deluſions; that whil'ſt with ſo much Rage they pretend to <hi>abhor Idols,</hi> they not only <hi>commit Sacriledg,</hi> but tread in the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of thoſe very Idolaters, <hi>they abhor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The head of that <hi>League</hi> was a <hi>young Duke;</hi> and our <hi>Aſſociators</hi> would not long have wanted <hi>one</hi> for theirs; Their youthful Leader was careſs'd and ſlattered with hopes of a Crown; grown <hi>Ambitious,</hi> by being <hi>Popular,</hi> and
<hi>diſcontented</hi> by <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet</hi> at Court; The
<hi>Toleration</hi> of <hi>Calviniſm</hi> was their ſpecious
<hi>Pretence</hi> for oppoſing the Government; The <hi>Connivance</hi> at
<hi>Popery</hi> is with us at preſent the ground for the ſame
<hi>Pretenſicus:</hi> The Names of <hi>Catholicks</hi> and <hi>Hugonots,</hi> were invented for diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating Parties by the <hi>Zealous Papiſt; Whigg,</hi> and <hi>Tory</hi> are ſet up now, for a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Saints by our <hi>Schiſmatical Phariſees:</hi> Our late
<hi>Remonſtrating</hi> and <hi>Proteſting,</hi> encouraged our
<hi>Contriver</hi> to venture on ſuch an <hi>Aſſociation; Remonſtrances,</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations</hi> uſhered in this their
<hi>Holy League.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:97305:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">French holy League.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Engliſh Aſſociation.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1 <hi>THat they would eſtabliſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the Law and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God in its priſtine State, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Form and Uſage of the Roman-Catholick Church.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1. I <hi>Protest to maintain, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend to the utmost of my Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the true Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, againſt Popery,</hi> &amp;c.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. <hi>Finding that our Enemies aim to eſtabliſh their Errors, we think it time to hinder their Plots and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>2. <hi>Finding to the grief of our Hearts, the Popiſh Prieſts, and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits have for many Years, purſued a moſt pernicious and helliſh Plot,</hi> &amp;c.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. <hi>That if there chance to be any Oppoſition made by any whomſoever, all the Confederates ſhall employ their Lives and Fortunes for deſtroying them by Arms.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3. <hi>But by force of Arms, if need ſo require; Expel, and Deſtroy all ſuch as ſhall adhere to him, or by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And purſue unto De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction all ſuch as ſhall oppoſe,</hi> &amp;c.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4. <hi>We ſwear by Almighty God, even to the laſt drop of our Blood, not to depart from this League upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Command, Pretence, Excuſe, or Occaſion whatſoever.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4. <hi>Neither will we for Perſons or Cauſes, Fear, or Reward, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate our ſelves from this Aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or fail in the proſecution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of during Lives.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5. <hi>We proteſt that if any of the Confederates be moleſted or troubled, all the reſt ſhall defend him,</hi> &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>5. <hi>With our joynt and particular Forces,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>to protect and defend all ſuch as ſhall enter into the juſt performance,</hi> &amp;c.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6. <hi>We entreat of what Condition ſoever to aſſiſt in the Proſecution of ſo good and pious a Work.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>6. <hi>We have thought to propoſe to all true Proteſtants an Union amongſt themſelves by ſolemn and ſacred Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Laſtly. <hi>Their League was ſubſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed underhand, by the greateſt part of the Commiſſioners of their Shires.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Laſtly. <hi>This Aſſociator ſwears to obey the major part of Members Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing this Aſſociation.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy Stateſmen,</hi> whoſe Plots and Actions run Parallel with thoſe of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite;</hi> and they good Men not ſo much as apprehenſive of the great Affinity that is between them; who with full Mouths, ignorantly <hi>follow</hi> the Chaſe they ſeem to <hi>fly</hi> from; and like eager Currs now and then run a little Counter: But yet I can't chuſe but ſmile, to ſee how the Faction hugs it ſelf, when ever any learned Pen, proves the Papiſt at the bottom of all theſe Deſigns, which of late has been by ſeveral en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured; Let but one of the
<hi>Regicides</hi> read ſuch a Pamphlet, it wipes its Mouth and all is well; thinks himſelf no <hi>Agent,</hi> not ſo much as an <hi>Abettor</hi> upon the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering this unknown <hi>Principal.</hi> Whatever Authors theſe are, I grant them their Aſſertions in ſome Caſes may be true, and their Deſign pretty honeſt; And in God's Name, let them paint out the
<hi>Conclave</hi> as black as <hi>Hell,</hi> and make their <hi>Plots</hi> as Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, as they would have their <hi>Religion;</hi> Let them leave not a
<hi>Conventicle</hi> or <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders-houſe</hi> without ſome diſguiſed
<hi>Prieſt</hi> or <hi>Jeſuit:</hi> Let them prove the <hi>Papiſts</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved the votes of <hi>Nonaddreſſes;</hi> and made it high Treaſon to <hi>Confer</hi> with their <hi>King;</hi> that it was they alone ordered the General to take <hi>Care</hi> of his <hi>Perſon,</hi> and call
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97305:16"/>a Council of War to draw up <hi>His Charge;</hi> that 'twas they paſſed an Act for his <hi>Trial,</hi> and a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> in the Vizzard cut off his Head<hi>:</hi> Laſtly that this <hi>Aſſociation</hi> was penned at <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſent over to the Confederates in a
<hi>Packet-Boat.</hi> All theſe things <hi>may be,</hi> but 'tis a bad Argument that they <hi>are,</hi> only becauſe they have a
<hi>Poſſibility</hi> of <hi>being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But grant that there is <hi>Great Evidence</hi> for all this, what is the work at preſent of ſome induſtrious Pens to prove. Theſe Popiſh inſtigations if plainly detected, will no more acquit our rebellious Male-contents, in a <hi>Moral ſenſe,</hi> than the diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Perſon that perſwades him to ſteal, will a Felon in <hi>Point of Law;</hi> and it ſeems to me a wild ſort of <hi>Indulgence</hi> that the
<hi>ſecret</hi> Practices of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, ſhould make the <hi>Open</hi> Rebellions of the <hi>Phanatick</hi> Party
<hi>Venial.</hi> If there are <hi>Jeſuits</hi> among them that buzz about theſe Elements of Treaſon, and Sedition; why muſt the Government be blamed for Connivance, and Pardoning thoſe Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains whom they themſelves protect from puniſhment? If a <hi>Prieſt</hi> that is <hi>Cloſe ſhaven</hi> ſhall commence a <hi>Godly Miniſter,</hi> aſſoon as his Locks can cover his <hi>Ears,</hi> muſt a Field Conventicle be pardoned when they are deluded into Rebellion, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe Father <hi>Greybeard</hi> put a trick upon them? Were they ſo deſirous to be really rid of thoſe Impoſtors, they would rather petition to have the Laws put in execution, than for <hi>Moderation</hi> and <hi>Repealing</hi> them. A louſie perſon that would willingly be rid of his troubleſom Vermine, will be willing to ſuffer the trouble of ſcouring too; and conſent to the buying a Bruſh, though it be for his own back<hi>:</hi> But theſe Logical heads give you a ſcrap of their <hi>Heereboord</hi> too, and talk of firſt taking away the
<hi>Cauſe,</hi> and then all the ſad <hi>Effects</hi> will preſently vaniſh. Very good, and the Government is about it as faſt as it can; but I am afraid were there not a <hi>Catholique</hi> left in the Nation, the whole Lump of <hi>Factious</hi> Leaven would remain ſtill. I know a
<hi>Monarch</hi> that denies the <hi>Popes</hi> Supremacy is as much in danger of being <hi>ſecretly</hi> ſtab'd by the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> as the
<hi>Prince</hi> that won't comply with his Malecontents is of being
<hi>Publickly</hi> butchered by the <hi>Phanatick;</hi> but I think it can't be collected from their Writings, that <hi>Monarchy</hi> it ſelf is ſuch a Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to the <hi>Conclave;</hi> but this I am ſure that nothing but a
<hi>Commonwealth</hi> can be gathered from the Doctrines of Mr.
<hi>Calvin.</hi> So that though they can prove the <hi>Pope</hi> to have had an hand in the <hi>Murder</hi> of our Royal Martyr, I am confident it will be an harder Task to prove his <hi>Holineſs</hi> helped up the following
<hi>Republick</hi> too; ſo that this Quaere will be the reſult; Whether the
<hi>Papiſts</hi> got the King murdered to ſet up the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Supremacy, or the <hi>Phanaticks</hi> to advance their own? In my Judgement thoſe bloody Politicks were as unſuitable to the ends of the <hi>One,</hi> as agreeable to the Deſigns of the <hi>Other;</hi> and I ſhould much
<hi>Diſtruſt</hi> the fam'd <hi>Subtilty</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> if he took ſo <hi>prepoſterous</hi> a Medium for purſuing his End. Whereas I admire the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks</hi> of our <hi>Republicans,</hi> who could never have reſolv'd on <hi>better</hi> Meaſures for theirs. And if
<hi>Succeſs</hi> can determine any thing, that darling <hi>Succeſs</hi> by which they juſtifyed all their Villanies; Then let them take their own
<hi>Minion</hi> and <hi>Favorite</hi> to decide the Controverſie; and ſhow whether the <hi>Pope</hi> was exalted here, or a <hi>Commonwealth.</hi> And
'tis a little improbable that the cunning <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> ſhould have taken all this Pains, only to ſhew himſelf notoriouſly wicked; and let the factious Spawn of <hi>Geneva</hi> reap the Benefit of all their impious Labours. Well, but the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> are certainly the <hi>Teazers,</hi> and <hi>Towzers,</hi> that ſet on a parcel of diſcontented People to worry the Government; And ought we not in Juſtice rather animadvert on thoſe that hollow them to the Sport, than on thoſe innocent Creatures, that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do what they are bidden? Since they are reſolved to have it ſo, wee'll grant the Suppoſition; but muſt I ſpit in the Mouth of that dangerous Curr, that fell upon me? And only bang the waggiſh Rogue that ſet him on? For my part, I ſhould think both deſerved a good Cudgelling. But what if this ſurly Creature be chained up by the Laws, to the good behaviour? And ſome tender hearted Souls, are for pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying the Confinement of this harmleſs Animal; <hi>for repealing of Statutes</hi> and ſlipping the Collar. Does the Papiſt do this too? and does he let him looſe <hi>to ſpoil the Aegyptians?</hi> I know the Tyrannies of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which we taſted and felt in the time of Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Perſecution, occaſioned the diſperſing of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſufferers into <hi>Franck-Fort</hi> and other parts of <hi>Germany;</hi> but why they were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to bring back from their travels only thoſe excellent accompliſhments of
<hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Sedition,</hi> I cannot apprehend. It would be a little ſcandalous to our nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>Particular,</hi> as well as to the
<hi>Reformed Religion</hi> in <hi>General,</hi> ſhould thoſe exiled Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of <hi>France,</hi> upon their return to their native Country have only learnt from our Engliſh to rebel.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:97305:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>I deſire no one to take this as the leaſt Vindication of the Papiſts; whom I look upon as ſuch Latitudinarians in Religion, and Morality, as need none of their wide
<hi>Diſpenſations,</hi> and <hi>Indulgences,</hi> to make them greater
<hi>Libertines;</hi> ſuch as are principl'd into greater <hi>Villanies</hi> (if any ſuch there be) than were committed by our late Rebels: The intent of this Digreſſion is only to correct thoſe, who by <hi>blackning</hi> the deep Deſigns and <hi>Endeavours</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> to Subvert our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, would waſh our Rebellious Negroes <hi>white,</hi> that
<hi>accompliſh't</hi> it. And 'tis time to give theſe Gentlemen a little Civil Correction, when they are thoſe of our <hi>own</hi> Clergy that merit it; That are come to flatter the <hi>very Schiſmatiques</hi> that diſturb their own Churches; As if it were only to prevent a <hi>Second Eject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or get a <hi>favourable Sequeſtration.</hi> Amongſt which ſort of meal-mouth'd Sycophants, we may reckon Mr. <hi>J. with his Daniels Den;</hi> the <hi>Philanglus</hi> with his <hi>Moderation,</hi> and Squire <hi>R.</hi> with his <hi>Julian Ship:</hi> I look on ſuch <hi>Secret</hi> Neutrals at preſent, as Dangerous, and Scandalous to the Church; As thoſe that
<hi>openly</hi> diſſent from it; Such as do it as great diſſervice as the wild Gentleman that put on a <hi>Gown,</hi> and <hi>Caſſock,</hi> and ran about Streets enquiring for a <hi>Whore:</hi> Such as han't that Kindneſs the Butchers Dog had for his Maſters meat, no not to the Church Government under which they live and officiate; But cloſe in with the invading Currs for a ſhare, inſtead of offering to defend it. I grant <hi>Moderation</hi> to be many times ſeaſonable; but not when Tranſgreſſors break the Laws moſt <hi>Immoderately:</hi> And thoſe obſtinate Antinomians from whom
<hi>Penalties</hi> cannot extert an obedience to the Laws, are very unlikely to be perſwaded with the <hi>Lenitives</hi> of <hi>Indulgence</hi> and
<hi>Toleration:</hi> And as for the plauſible Arguments they uſe to perſuade our Church to <hi>Condeſcention; viz.</hi> becauſe of the Dangers that threaten us from <hi>Rome;</hi> That ſure may be a better Motive (one would think) only for their <hi>Conformity:</hi> When the <hi>one</hi> muſt be done by <hi>repealing old</hi> Canons, and making <hi>new</hi> ones; the other only by <hi>Conforming</hi> to thoſe <hi>already</hi> made: The one a <hi>yielding</hi> of thoſe that have the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and
<hi>Man,</hi> on their ſide; The other of thoſe that have <hi>neither,</hi> and in ſome ſenſe a ſort of <hi>Out-Laws.</hi> Neither have we any Security, theſe froward Gentlemen would be pleas'd, ſhould they be
<hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor'd</hi> too. The peeviſh Lady that makes her indulgent Lover cut off the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſcency of hair, and beard, or the ſuperfluities of his over-grown <hi>Muſtachoes,</hi> as Mr. <hi>A.</hi> that <hi>Proteſtant Droll,</hi> and <hi>gifted Buffoon,</hi> reſembles our Ceremonies to; may upon the next frisk of petulancy requeſt the poor man to flea himſelf alive, or lopp away a Limb. And what manner of yielding and condeſcention they expect, may be gather'd from the Paper of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> that was ſpread abroad at Coffee-Houſes, when the Parliament ſate laſt at
<hi>London;</hi> to whoſe conſideration it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to be preſented: An <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> little better than that propos'd in the
<hi>Scotch Covenant;</hi> By total Extirpation of Epiſcopal Government: And for Succouring the Church at preſent againſt Popery, is but a meer ſhamming Argument: For 'tis Evident they had rather ſee it ruin'd by
<hi>Turks,</hi> or <hi>Mahometans,</hi> than ſtrike one blow to prevent it. And 'tis no good Policy, for any man, though aſſaulted by a <hi>Lion,</hi> to let looſe a <hi>Bear</hi> for his aſſiſtance: It is alſo a diſhoneſt, and impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſort of diffidence for any to diſtruſt the now Eſtabliſh't Government, as not able to ſupport it ſelf without ſuch dangerous alliance which has once already ſerv'd the Church, as ſome Confederates have done their Neighbouring Allies, ſubdued thoſe they pretended to aſſiſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Law</hi> certainly is the greateſt, and only Pillar to ſupport the Church, and State; And it was the Obſervation of as Eminent a Perſon as ever was <hi>in it;</hi> That none ever wreſtl'd with it, but in the end it infallibly broke their Necks. There was never more occaſion for its vigorous Execution; And 'tis no ſuch Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> repreſents it, to puniſh Diſſenters with a Priſon, when ſome of them have been willing to croud thither, only to make up a Conventicle; perverting the very <hi>Penalties</hi> of the Law, to a further
<hi>opportunity</hi> of <hi>breaking</hi> it; and making that ſubſervient to the <hi>Crime,</hi> which was intended to <hi>correct</hi> it. This Animadverſion on our Diſſenters, and their Advocates, is both pertinent to this Diſcourſe, and favourable to thoſe it reflects on: The one, becauſe 'tis certain their Faction is concern'd in this
<hi>Aſſociation.</hi> The other, becauſe ſuch offenders deſerve to be more ſeverely handled.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:97305:17"/>And now you ſhall ſee the Diſparity between a <hi>True Patriot,</hi> and a <hi>Factious Aſſociator;</hi> the difference there is betwixt one that truly Loves his Countrey, and him that only pretends it.</p>
            <p>A True <hi>Patriot,</hi> will endeavor the <hi>Peace</hi> and Quietneſs of the Kingdom wherein he Lives; and if he ſits at Helm, will ſo ſteer the Bark, that it may fail ſecurely in the midſt of the greateſt danger; neither ſplit on the Rocks that threaten it on
<hi>one</hi> ſide; Or running into the Quick-ſand, that would caſt her away on the <hi>other;</hi> will endeavour to preſerve the Nation from the
<hi>Popery</hi> we <hi>fear,</hi> and from the <hi>Fanaticiſm</hi> we have
<hi>felt:</hi> One that has helpt to make it flouriſh in Peace and Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty this <hi>Twenty Years;</hi> And will endeavour to keep it in the ſame Proſperity <hi>ſtill.</hi> One, that will with Equal Courage reſiſt an
<hi>Engliſh Rebellion,</hi> that he would a <hi>Spaniſh Invaſion:</hi> That won't endeavour to ſatisfie <hi>every</hi> diſcontended grumbler; but remove all <hi>real</hi> motives to complaint and murmuring: That will
<hi>keep</hi> to the Rules of <hi>Law,</hi> and Juſtice, as the beſt means to <hi>keep</hi> the <hi>Peace</hi> too: Free from all Paſſion and Intereſt; and ſo can neither trouble the Kingdom, by the
<hi>Turbulency</hi> of the <hi>one;</hi> or defraud it by the
<hi>Temptations</hi> of the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Factious <hi>Aſſociator,</hi> makes it his buſineſs to
<hi>diſturb</hi> the Countrey wherein he Lives, with as much Fear and Jealouſie, as Thought can ſuggeſt, or Malice invent; for 'tis Quietneſs and Peace that makes him idle and without Employ: 'Tis a ſort of
<hi>Sea-Monſter,</hi> that ſhows himſelf moſt before a Storm; And endeavors to <hi>overſet</hi> that Ship, which he is not Capacitated to
<hi>Steer.</hi> His Eyes are ſet on the Publique Miniſters of State, not to
<hi>pry</hi> into their <hi>Actions,</hi> but <hi>murder</hi> their
<hi>Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations:</hi> Not to ſearch them like an <hi>Eagle,</hi> but to ſacrifice them like a <hi>Baſilisk.</hi> 'Tis a State <hi>Cannibal</hi> that delights in <hi>blood;</hi> and triumphs in the Miſeries of a Civil War. One that makes <hi>Religion</hi> a pretence for <hi>Rebellion;</hi> Though as
<hi>empty</hi> of the one, as <hi>brim full</hi> of the other. One that would fluſh himſelf in the Spoils of a <hi>New</hi> War; though glutted almoſt with the blood that was ſhed in the <hi>Old.</hi> 'Tis the <hi>rarified Chamaeleon,</hi> That out-does the <hi>natural</hi> one; feeds <hi>not</hi> ſo much as upon <hi>Air,</hi> But only <hi>Popular breath:</hi> Sets the Nation all in <hi>Combuſtion;</hi> and then like a ſecure
<hi>Salamander,</hi> lives in the <hi>flame.</hi> One that ſeems <hi>Hells Purveyor,</hi> and like the <hi>Devil</hi> makes his <hi>Covenanting Imps</hi> ſubſcribe their Contracts <hi>in their own blood:</hi> That <hi>Sails</hi> ſecurely by tacking about with Wind, and Tide; and <hi>expoſes</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to be <hi>ſhatter'd</hi> in the Tempeſt: That talks of nothing but the <hi>Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Body <hi>Politick;</hi> only becauſe his <hi>Natural</hi> one <hi>pines</hi> with diſcontent.</p>
            <p>The <hi>one</hi> will with an earneſt, even anxious ſollicitation of mind, ſeek to <hi>reconcile</hi> the jarring hearts of Subjects to their Lawful Prince; Let them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the goodneſs and equity of the merciful King that governs; will help his <hi>gracious Monarch,</hi> to make all manner of good impreſſion on his
<hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects;</hi> and give his people all imaginable ſatisfaction; will perſwade them to acquieſce with his Majeſty's reaſons for diſſolving an old Parliament, and his Gracious promiſes for calling a
<hi>new</hi> one; that will <hi>thank</hi> him for ſuch kind Aſſurances and Declaration; and not <hi>extenuate</hi> ſo gracious an action, with a talk of <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Obligation;</hi> will open the <hi>blind</hi> eyes of the deluded <hi>Rabble,</hi> and take away the Veil of Popularity, that
<hi>blinds</hi> the diſcontented <hi>great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>other</hi> purſues with the greateſt aggravation, the leaſt ſlip in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, <hi>ſtirs up</hi> Jealouſies and Animoſities between King and People, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the <hi>Reconciliation</hi> that would otherwiſe enſue; for then the little Artifices he uſes to foment Sedition would be illuded; and his Engines of Rebellion, <hi>Libels, Aſſociations, Remonstrances,</hi> would grow ruſty, and uſeleſs: He is bound in prudence to make the <hi>Peoples</hi> Cauſe his <hi>Own;</hi> and for his ſecurity, to be guarded by his Whifflers the Rabble; is grieved and afflicted, when the King <hi>comforts</hi> his People; perverts the
<hi>best</hi> things, to the <hi>worſt</hi> ſenſe; daubs and
<hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figures</hi> all with his <hi>Colours,</hi> which is like to
<hi>wipe</hi> off the pretence and <hi>Varniſh</hi> of his <hi>Cauſe;</hi> cavils at the <hi>Declaration</hi> of his <hi>Prince,</hi> becauſe intended to ſatisfie the <hi>People;</hi> proves the Parliament
<hi>unreaſonably</hi> diſſolved, becauſe the King gives good
<hi>reaſon</hi> for it; makes the Nation believe it ſhall <hi>never</hi> ſee another, when the<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97305:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>he Declaration promiſes the
<hi>contrary;</hi> but yet thinks ſit to <hi>extort</hi> it from the King by Petition, for fear it ſhould paſs otherwiſe for his <hi>Gratious</hi> action; deludes the ſilly <hi>Mobile,</hi> with expectations of being
<hi>great,</hi> and perſwades the <hi>Nobility,</hi> they are not truly ſo without a <hi>Popular</hi> greatneſs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>one</hi> is for the <hi>uniting</hi> the people in
<hi>affection</hi> and <hi>charity,</hi> if he can't ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it in
<hi>Perſwaſion</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> won't multiply foes by
<hi>Suſpition,</hi> or create dangers out of a <hi>Panick</hi> fear; one that will never hugg a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot as tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the Nurſing-Father of it, a <hi>Jeſuit;</hi> No ſuch <hi>Ambidexter,</hi> as to make a
<hi>Bugbear</hi> and <hi>Darling</hi> of the ſame thing, and both equally ſubſervient to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; No ſuch <hi>mimical Ape,</hi> as with
<hi>diſtorting,</hi> ſquinting looks, ridicules every thing in his
<hi>countenance,</hi> that does not ſuit with his froward <hi>Genius:</hi> He is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect piece of <hi>ſincerity,</hi> and never makes a
<hi>Juglers-box</hi> of his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down
<hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and bringing up nothing but Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable <hi>Covenants</hi> and <hi>Aſſociations;</hi> like thoſe <hi>Impoſtors</hi> that are ſeen to let down but
<hi>harmleſs Tape,</hi> and <hi>Ribband,</hi> yet diſgorge <hi>Knives,</hi> and <hi>Daggers.</hi> He will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Lawful Authority of the
<hi>State,</hi> and conform to the conſtant Diſcipline of the
<hi>Church;</hi> will with an awful reſpect look upon the <hi>Crown,</hi> and pay his due reverence to the <hi>Mitre;</hi> will oppoſe the Toleration of
<hi>all</hi> Religion, as the ready way to have <hi>none;</hi> He will
<hi>truly</hi> ſtand up for the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the Subject, and not make it a <hi>pretence</hi> to <hi>enſlave</hi> them; One that will
<hi>truſt</hi> his Prince with Money, for the ſupport of his Crown and Dignity, and <hi>allow</hi> him a competent <hi>Guard,</hi> for the preſervation of his Perſon; One that will <hi>ſwear</hi> Allegiance to
<hi>none,</hi> but his King; And laſtly, never out of fear of a
<hi>contingent</hi> danger, will raiſe a <hi>preſent</hi> War for altering Succeſſion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>other</hi> is ſo far from <hi>reconciling</hi> differences in <hi>Religion,</hi> that he can hardly admit of a good opinion of any, not of his own <hi>ſentiments;</hi> tranſubſtantiates his <hi>Sword of the Spirit,</hi> into that of <hi>Steel;</hi> and makes his Church truly
<hi>Militant,</hi> by being in Arms; <hi>crys</hi> down the Plot, at the ſame time he makes it <hi>ſupport</hi> his Cauſe; Pulls at the <hi>Tripple Crown</hi> with <hi>one</hi> hand, and the King's <hi>Scepter</hi> with the
<hi>other:</hi> The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Virtuoſo, that views the ſlips of Government in a <hi>Microſcope;</hi> and ſo magniſies the <hi>biting</hi> of a <hi>Flea,</hi> to the <hi>pinching</hi> of a <hi>Lobster;</hi> And for his tranſubſtantiating of Mettals, and Chymical knacks, exceeds the
<hi>Dutch</hi> Van Helmont, or our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Boyle; with a little
<hi>Panegyrick</hi> can <hi>Sublime</hi> a <hi>knave</hi> to the very Quinteſſence of <hi>honeſty;</hi> and then with one <hi>drop</hi> of the venom of his tongue, <hi>debaſe</hi> him to the worſt of <hi>villains;</hi> Can devour a <hi>Test,</hi> and belch up a <hi>Remonſtrance;</hi> So refractory an Animal as to oppoſe the <hi>Government</hi> in all its actions, and the <hi>Church</hi> in every Canon and Conſtitution; Inſtead of
<hi>reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting</hi> the Crown, <hi>tramples</hi> it under feet: Makes the countenancing <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> an expedient for ſuppreſſing
<hi>Popery;</hi> And the <hi>rooting</hi> out of Superſtition, the means of
<hi>introducing</hi> Schiſm, and Diviſion; Makes the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Subject</hi> a pretence to <hi>depoſe</hi> the <hi>Prince,</hi> and
<hi>enſlave</hi> the <hi>People;</hi> And is only for <hi>repealing</hi> the Laws, that he himſelf may be the greater <hi>Libertine,</hi> and rebel with a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe; Is for removing thoſe terrible <hi>Guards,</hi> becauſe they
<hi>preſerve</hi> his Majeſty's Perſon, and loves to keep his Prince
<hi>poor,</hi> out of hopes to make him <hi>contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible;</hi> Inſtead of acknowledging the <hi>King</hi>'s Supremacy, ſwears to <hi>obey Members,</hi> and fellow Subjects; Out of dread of a <hi>future</hi> alteration in the
<hi>Church,</hi> will make a <hi>preſent</hi> change in the <hi>State;</hi> And will <hi>actually</hi> raiſe War againſt the right Heir of the Crown, only becauſe he can't very <hi>formally</hi> diſ-inherit him.</p>
            <p>And now becauſe the D. gives this <hi>Aſſociator</hi> all his pretences for ſuch a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Combination; I ſhall in <hi>this very Caſe</hi> prove him but a <hi>diſguis'd</hi> Patriot; and that the Mediums he has propos'd to himſelf, demonſtrate him rather a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous
<hi>Hun,</hi> than a true Roman <hi>Brutus;</hi> A <hi>cruel Scourge</hi> to his Countrey, more than a <hi>tender Lover</hi> of it. And firſt for thoſe reaſons of State, and Self-preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, which he would have to warrant this total Excluſion, expelling and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying his <hi>Highneſs:</hi> (ſaving the reſpect I bear to the <hi>Author</hi> and his politick Noddle) I think they may paſs rather for Proverbial Sentences, and expreſſions
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97305:18"/>of <hi>private</hi> reſentment, than Maxims of true Policy; and Aphoriſms of undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed truth for the <hi>Countreys</hi> good; For though I never much conſulted Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Holy Common-wealth,</hi> or <hi>William Pryn</hi>'s <hi>Popiſh Royal Favorite;</hi> Yet I can't think the deſtroying the <hi>One</hi> muſt be warrantable, becauſe we have a mind to ſet up the <hi>Other;</hi> Or that a
<hi>Popiſh Succeſſor</hi> muſt be <hi>ruin'd,</hi> for the
<hi>eſtabliſhing</hi> a <hi>Republick;</hi> neither can I underſtand why this excluſion, muſt be Judg'd ſuch an abſolute demonſtration of a mans Love to his Countrey; ſo meritorious a piece of Piety; That it can not onely expiate for all the blood, murder and devaſtation, which may be the conſequences; but juſtifie this very villanous <hi>Aſſociator,</hi> in endeavouring to exclude him by <hi>himſelf;</hi> Or the aſſiſtance of his Confederates, without the ſuppos'd legal proceſs, of an Act of
<hi>Parliament.</hi> Certainly he is not to be eſteem'd a prudent adviſer for his Countreys good, that <hi>onely means</hi> well to it; That adviſes a good thing, but ſuch as would have the unhappy concomitancy of a greater
<hi>ill.</hi> If they make the <hi>Parliament</hi> the ſole Arbitrators of the publick good; I mean thoſe whom they commonly take for it, the Lower Houſe<hi>:</hi> yet they are not (under favour) to tranſcribe their ſentiments into practice, and reſolve on expelling that by force, which their <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> could not obtain by requeſt. If they are Commenc'd alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſuch Caſuiſtical Libertines; Then the
<hi>preſent</hi> eſtabliſhment of Church and State, is to me as much a Miracle, as ever was the <hi>Restoring it.</hi> And on the ſame ground they may muſter up their Train-Bands, march to <hi>White-hall,</hi> reform the Council with the puſh of Pike; from thence to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and cudgel thoſe Arbitrary Judges into better underſtanding of the Laws; And then back with ſome Captain <hi>Hickeringill</hi> to <hi>Doctors Commons;</hi> and blow up all the Enemies to <hi>Naked Truth,</hi> or teach them at leaſt to keep their Eccleſiaſtical Courts in better order; And all theſe things very lawful, becauſe under conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the Parliament. I know the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inheriting the D. with a <hi>Bill</hi> of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion will by many be thought a <hi>pretty</hi> ſort of
<hi>Expedient;</hi> But the deſtroying him without one, muſt by all, be counted a <hi>Damnable Rebellion;</hi> muſt involve the Nation in Blood; Purple agen her Rivers with the Slain, and make our wretched Iſle ſeem to float once more in her red Sea; Expoſe the poor Subject to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs Sword; and all the Miſeries of a Civil War. And now Quaere Whether this Aſſociator's Love to his King, or his Countrey out-weigh each other by ſo much as a grain? The very <hi>diſ-inheriting</hi> him <hi>with</hi> a
<hi>Bill,</hi> may have Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces bad enough; how much more then the
<hi>reſisting</hi> him <hi>without?</hi> An Excluded Prince, though with form of Juſtice, will find Adherents. One would think theſe <hi>bad Politicians,</hi> ſhould be <hi>worſe Hiſtorians</hi> too; And not ſo much as have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted the Chronicles of their <hi>own</hi> Nation; which has already miſerably felt, and that <hi>more</hi> than once, the Bloody Conſequences of a debarr'd Right. Of which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy <hi>Wounds,</hi> the reproaching <hi>Scars</hi> upbraid us to our <hi>very</hi> Faces, and to this
<hi>very</hi> day; I hope Parallels in <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> need not be ſo Mathematical as thoſe in <hi>Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try:</hi> And though I can't give an inſtance of a Duke of <hi>York</hi> that was <hi>Excluded</hi> from his Right; yet it may ſuffice, if I tell you of one that after much Blood
<hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd</hi> it. There has been a <hi>Parliament</hi> that has Excluded the right Line, to make way for a pretended one; depos'd their <hi>King,</hi> and accepted an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> (not to mention the more Barbarous Proceedings of later Times, when they murder'd a <hi>Mighty Monarch,</hi> and made an <hi>Arch-Rebel</hi> mount the Throne.) We had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that a Prince
<hi>Depos'd</hi> with as much Authority of Parliament as this can be
<hi>Debar'd:</hi> We had one at <hi>least</hi> of the <hi>Houſe</hi> of
<hi>York</hi> Voted out of his Throne, but yet (as if Vengeance which is ſaid to follow lamely, had mended her pace) 'tis obſerveable, That <hi>only</hi> Three <hi>Lancasters,</hi> the Fourth, Fifth and Sixth <hi>Henry</hi> ſucceſſively Reign'd, and maintain'd the Uſurpation; Of which one was a
<hi>Mon-mouth</hi> too; and all the dear Conqueſts was by the <hi>latter</hi> of theſe quite loſt, which had been bought by ſo much Blood by the
<hi>former:</hi> And the very Crown too Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the Head of an <hi>Excluded Duke of York;</hi> And the then preſent King only Complemented with a
<hi>durante vitâ;</hi> and the bare formality of wearing it: I have ſo little Kindneſs for <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> or <hi>Superſtition,</hi> That I lay but ſmall ſtreſs on the Jingling Homonymie, or agreeable found of the names; Neither looking on them as Ominous or Prophetick: Though I believe would they make for<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97305:18"/>ſome peoples turns, they would be better weigh'd, and ſifted; made uſe of as preſages, and fore-bodings of
<hi>good</hi> Succeſs; whereas we only ſee it had a very <hi>bad</hi> one. I confeſs they have an Argument <hi>now</hi> for altering the Succeſſion, which they wanted <hi>then; viz.</hi> the <hi>different perſuaſion in Religion;</hi> whereas they Depos'd <hi>Richard</hi> the Second <hi>only</hi> for a pretended unworthineſs, unprofitableneſs, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency: But yet I think the <hi>contingent</hi> danger of parting with our Reform'd Religion, can never warrant a certain involving the Nation in the Miſeries of a Civil War. I conceive, if we are Chriſtians, 'tis no ſuch abſurd thing to rely upon Providence too: And though this <hi>Aſſociator</hi> makes Queen <hi>Marys</hi> Caſe ſuch an abſolute Argument of Popery being introduc'd; I muſt beg leave to obſerve to him his prepoſterous Logick and Reaſoning, to be but proving an <hi>abſolute</hi> and
<hi>univerſal</hi> Poſition, from a <hi>ſingle,</hi> and
<hi>particular</hi> inſtance; And thoſe Laws then Enacted had never ſo many <hi>Proviſo</hi>'s againſt the introducing that Religion, as perhaps His Majeſty would have yielded to, had they but accepted of thoſe Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Tenders for <hi>Limiting</hi> the <hi>Succeſſor.</hi> I know the plauſible Argument is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on very ſmoothly; and ſlips in with a whole heap of Syllogiſms; <hi>If a Popiſh Prince, then a Popiſh Council; If a Popiſh Council, then ſure Popiſh Biſhops; If Popiſh Biſhops, then the Popiſh Maſs too.</hi> But I can tell them of a more Experienc'd ſort of <hi>Sorites,</hi> a ſadder heap of Argumentation; And already prov'd by frequent Induction; <hi>If we find a Factious City, then a Factious Sheriff; If a Factious Sheriff, then a Factious Jury; If a Factious Jury, then all the Factious Fellows are acquitted.</hi> I confeſs they have made the Argument pretty <hi>ſtrong,</hi> by ſhowing themſelves the
<hi>Buttereſs</hi> to ſupport it.</p>
            <p>But what if I ſhould barr the neceſſity of theſe
<hi>Concluſions</hi> from the <hi>Premiſes,</hi> I think I ſhould be very
<hi>Civil</hi> to <hi>Them,</hi> and <hi>Juſt</hi> to the Caſe of the
<hi>Succeſſor.</hi> Suppoſe if from this <hi>Factious</hi> City, the King ſhould take his <hi>Gracious</hi> Charter; The City may be Factious ſtill;
<hi>without</hi> a Sheriff, <hi>without</hi> a Jury, <hi>without</hi> the fearful Lirry of many ſuch unhappy Conſequences. And then with
<hi>Reaſonable</hi> men there is always the ſame <hi>reaſon</hi> for Contraries; Suppoſe if from a <hi>Popiſh Prince</hi> there is ſo much of Prerogative taken away, as when parted with, will put him out of a capacity of impoſing his Religion on his Subjects; He may ſtill be the ſame
<hi>Popiſh Prince; without</hi> Popiſh Council, <hi>without</hi> Popiſh Biſhops, and <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> their Popiſh Maſs and Religion being obtruded on the Nation. And theſe ſort of Expedients have been as
<hi>Graciouſly</hi> tender'd, as <hi>ſtrangely</hi> rejected; And our careful Patriots not being able <hi>thoroughly</hi> (as they call it) to ſecure us, and the Nation by a <hi>Total Excluſion,</hi> in Kindneſs, and order to its Preſervation, will accept of <hi>no Mediums</hi> at all: If this be the beſt Politicks of this Age, I fancy the ador'd <hi>Matchiavil</hi> and the Writings of the beſt Stateſmen are unhappily loſt, or little conſulted. But as for the deep Deſign, and Helliſh Contrivance of this
<hi>Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciator,</hi> no doubt they are Politick Meaſures, and Zealous Endeavours for his Countreys good; The putting it all in a <hi>Flame,</hi> no doubt will purge off all the <hi>Droſs</hi> of Superſtition, and Idolatry; and leave nothing behind it of <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> beſides the
<hi>Tyranny</hi> of the <hi>refined</hi> holy Common-wealth. And this is the Drift of this diſguiſed <hi>Aſſociator</hi> and pretended
<hi>Patriot;</hi> This <hi>Religious State-Bully,</hi> That can cheat the Nation with the <hi>Maſque</hi> of Holyneſs, and meer <hi>Vizard</hi> of Piety, and make Three <hi>Zealous</hi> Kingdoms <hi>devoutly periſh,</hi> even in working out their own <hi>Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be objected I have made too wide Inferences; And that ſuch an <hi>Aſſociation</hi> may not have all thoſe bad Conſequences we ſeem to dread from its being carried on; I deſire ſuch Gentlemen to conſider, That there is no Villany but may be comprehended Lawful under ſuch a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Pretence; And when the old <hi>Covenants</hi> were ſworn to, ſome of the very Subſcribers never imagin'd they would have prov'd ſuch <hi>Flood-Gates</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> and let in ſuch a
<hi>deluge</hi> of <hi>Impiety, Treaſon,</hi> and <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> And what leſs can be expected from ſuch a Combination at <hi>this</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:97305:19"/>time, Than the Subverſion of <hi>Church,</hi> and
<hi>State?</hi> when they are come to
<note n="*" place="margin">In the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Kings Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> fancy <hi>Statute Laws inſignificant, unleſs the very Rabble ſet up for the ſole Magiſtrates and Legiſlators;</hi> And all Eccleſiaſtical Canons, Rites and Ceremonies; The meer Fopperies of
<hi>Rome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and as a <hi>ſort of ſuperfluous Excreſcencies</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Mr. <hi>A.</hi> in his miſchief of Impoſitions.</note> 
               <hi>of hair, and beard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> And what other way is there left for the ſtopping theſe <hi>Sluces</hi> of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and <hi>Schiſm;</hi> But by guarding the <hi>Churches Vine</hi> from the
<hi>Wild Boar of the Forreſt;</hi> And defending our <hi>Royal Oak</hi> from being again <hi>cut down with an Ax?</hi> This alone can ſuperſede the ſad Completion of the Parable of <hi>Trees; Keep the Fire from coming out of the Brambles, and devouring the Cedars of</hi> Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
